<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The loving husband and prudent wife represented in the persons of St. Eustachius and Theopista, martyrs / written in Italian by John Baptista Manzini and Englished by John Burbery.</title>
            <author>Manzini, Giovanni Battista, 1599-1664.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 174 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 107 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51875</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M556</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29503</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11156784</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11156784</idno>
            <idno type="VID">46454</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51875)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 46454)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1425:31)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The loving husband and prudent wife represented in the persons of St. Eustachius and Theopista, martyrs / written in Italian by John Baptista Manzini and Englished by John Burbery.</title>
                  <author>Manzini, Giovanni Battista, 1599-1664.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 203 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. Martin and J. Allestrye,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The historie is confirmed by Baronius with the testimony of Greek and Latin authors."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Eustace, --  Saint, martyr, d. 118.</term>
               <term>Theophista, --  Martyr.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:46454:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE LOVING HUSBAND, And Prudent WIFE; Repreſented in the perſons of St. <hi>Euſtachius</hi> and <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſta,</hi> Martyrs.</p>
            <p>Written in Italian by <hi>John Baptiſta Manzini,</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhed by <hi>John Burbery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Hiſtorie is confirmed by <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronius,</hi> with the teſtimony of Greek and Latine Authors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>J. Martin,</hi> and <hi>J. Alleſtrye,</hi> at the Bell in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Churchyard, 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:46454:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46454:2"/>
            <head>To the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable Pair, and no leſs happy in affection, than matchleſs in worth, and honour, the Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable <hi>Henry Howard</hi> of <hi>Arundell,</hi> my moſt noble Patron, and the Ladie <hi>Anne</hi> his Wife.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>IS related of the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Alphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> that by ſubter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranean
<pb facs="tcp:46454:3"/>paſſages, it runs awhile un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen through the Countrey of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,</hi> but afterwards breaking out, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairs to the Sea, though with no great ſtream. The rivulet of my thanks (for your favour to me, all along my atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance
<pb facs="tcp:46454:3"/>on my Lords of happy memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, your Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father, and Father, and ſince more abundantly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd during my ſervice with your Honours) which long hath been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd, (it having no proportion with the Sea of your
<pb facs="tcp:46454:4"/>bounty) now open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly runs thither, though bluſhing all the way, at the ſmallneſs of the ſtream. But ſince at any rate I deſire to be gratefull to your Honours, (I publiſhing with my gratitude my own imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) whom can I
<pb facs="tcp:46454:4"/>more worthily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>title to this Book, ſince the one is ſo loving a Husband, and the other ſo prudent a Wife? The Dedication then by right be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to your Honours, (Valour and Beauty, with the virtues of both Sexes, meeting in
<pb facs="tcp:46454:5"/>you, as lines in the center) what juſter Oblation could be made, if the Offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring had reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance with your Honours high de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts? But the Sun not ſecluding the Valleys from the influence of his rayes, invites me to hope, your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours
<pb facs="tcp:46454:5"/>(like the Sun in the luſter of your Families) will deſcend into this Valley, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude not from the influence of your favourable aſpect, the humble la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honours moſt devoted, and moſt faithfull humble Servant,</hi> John Burbery.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:46454:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:46454:6"/>
            <head>The Loving Husband, and Prudent Wife, &amp;c.</head>
            <div n="1" type="book">
               <head>The firſt Book.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE merit of Virtue is ſo great, and ſo glorious with Man, that if Man ow'd not Virtue to God, he would owe leſs to God than to Virtue. And what benefit would Life be, if Life were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but a bundle of evils? A good life, ſaid the Moraliſt, is a greater benefit than life it ſelf. The merit of Virtue (a Treaſure
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:46454:7"/>we have happily gotten out of the Exchequer of Gods grace) is the thing that hath made Man admir'd many times above all earthly Creatures. And what wonder is it, that an Angel, whoſe object is ſo bleſſed, and whoſe nature ſo perfect, ſhould alwayes live burning in the love of that Creator he beholds and enjoyes? A wonder it is, and a wonder for a Deity, that is ſeated on a Throne of Omnipotency, to ſee that a worm of the earth, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd with the weight of his carnal deſires, wreſtling with the diſtraction of ſo many flattering objects, and oppos'd by Hells treacheries and power, ſhould be every where invincible, and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphing over all dangers, by a heat of love, mount above the ſphear of all corporeal things on the wings of Charity; and flying into the boſome of his Maker, miraculouſly engraff, and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:46454:7"/>himſelf wholly into his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. If the reverence (due to the profound depths of heavenly wiſdome) commanded not my ſilence, I ſhould preſume to ſay, that to ſo rebellious an Angel as <hi>Lucifer,</hi> a man ſo pious as he I ſpeak of, ſhould in reaſon have been Guardian. Perhaps his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample might have kept him in his duty, who hath rear'd with a handfull of Clay, an Altar to his God, to the ſhame of a noble ſpirit, whoſe ſacriledges laſted but a while, to make him more emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent in his ſin, than his nature.</p>
               <p>Of ſuch men renowned for Virtue, the Stories of Chriſtian Religion relate many. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe to arrive at the perfection of ſo holy a ſtate, Virtue is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, and cannot be better learned than by an Example, I have thought it fit to give the Reader a Pattern, which we by imitation may improve to our advantage.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:46454:8"/>
               <p>In the life of <hi>Euſtachius</hi> you will reade the Idea of Perfection. His Heart was Love's Forge; his Boſome a Shop of Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Whatever we believe of all the Unfortunate, we may pity in <hi>Euſtachius</hi> alone. His life made him a Martyr, perhaps too a greater than his death; yea nothing but onely death hath contributed to his reſt, among the intollerable and unceſſant tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ſo painfull a life. Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever hath not read his life, knows not yet how God playes at Tennis. <hi>Job</hi> in the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment would have been Envie's ſubject, if <hi>Euſtachius</hi> had not been born. <hi>Euſtachius</hi> hindred <hi>Job</hi> from being ſingular, and <hi>Job</hi> him from being the firſt. Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever gives not credit to Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, let him forbear reading this Story; in which it's a Miracle to me, my heart doth not break in running it over, much more in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:46454:8"/>writing it. He that denſes Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation in a good man is a gift of God, ſhall ſee by reading here, whether it were poſſible a man of ill life could ſuffer, without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair, the thouſandth part of the diſaſters of this heart without heart. I call the heart of <hi>Euſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius</hi> a heart without heart, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing Chriſt did there the office of a heart. And I cannot think it poſſible, that had not God aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted particularly, he could have oppoſed, much more overcome the power of Hell, ſo much at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and ſet on to ruine him, who being onely fleſh, in the end would have ſhewed his weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p>Of the Father of <hi>Euſtachius,</hi> his Nativity, and Countrey, we have no light at all from Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; were it that the Writers employ'd about the miracles of his life, had no leiſure to celebrate his birth; or were it, that God
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:46454:9"/>(being alwayes myſterious) would not let him be known to deſcend from the Earth, whom he had predeſtin'd to be a great Ornament to his Heaven, and our Law. It's the fate of the famous Rivers, <hi>Euphrates</hi> and <hi>Tygris,</hi> to derive their ſprings from Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe.</p>
               <p>He was born, and liv'd long in the errours of the Gentiles, and barbarous Infidels: but true it is alſo, that in the whole car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of his life, nothing could be ever obſerv'd to be barbarous, but his Paganiſm. He liv'd in <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jan</hi>'s time, God would not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit him, or his Prince, to be born in an age of impiety. <hi>Trajan</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd to be born in a time when the juſtice of his Faith muſt be purg'd, as that of his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But Almighty God, who was pleas'd to try his Church, to make it victorious, deſign'd that age for Princes, the hardneſs of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:46454:9"/>whoſe hearts was to ſerve for a reſemblance with the mines of a riſing Faith.</p>
               <p>He was called <hi>Placidus</hi> from his Cradle, perhaps with leſs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of his mildneſs than his happineſs. Even his name aſſur'd him, he ſhould be very accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to God.</p>
               <p>Being born in a Countrey (if we may believe his valour, which perſwades us to think he was a Roman) and in an age that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced all Virtues to Courage, he went to the Wars, to train up his Youth in the School of <hi>Mars.</hi> In a ſhort ſpace of time, his Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour was ſo cry'd up by all, that he (like another <hi>Leonides</hi>) was ſuppoſed to have a hairy heart in his breaſt. In dangers he was greater than dangers, and leſs onely than his own Gallantry, which was ſway'd by his Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence alone. The Souldiers had him alwayes for a object to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:46454:10"/>the Commanders for a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to commend, and the Enemy for a Thunderbolt to fear.</p>
               <p>If he fought, he overcame; and if he conquer'd, he fought not. He never ſhew'd more valour, than when he had occaſion to pardon; and never more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly pardon'd, than when the Enemy deſpair'd more of Pardon than Victory. He rejoyced in conquering, not in killing; and onely then kill'd, when Clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy was Cruelty, or dangerous. He was not enamour'd of a great, but good report; neither mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd he his Victories by the ſpace the Dead took up, but that the Suppliants fill'd. To affirm, he had a calm minde; it is enough to ſay, his minde would never yield to be conquer'd. He that is magnanimous, loves Victories, and not Slaughters. Whoſoever ſpills blood with delight, may well boaſt of being a valorous
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:46454:10"/>Tiger, but cannot be a Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier.</p>
               <p>As he went not temerariouſly to the Wars, but was invited thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Glory; ſo his forward ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit never engag'd him in their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours; who running more impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly than warily after Fame, fall into a thouſand precipices. His good ſervice, and prudence, gave him preſently the character of a worthy Commander; which the Emperour hearing of, he was not long a Pretender to Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the Armies, whoſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt part he was. His ſingular Valour more advanc'd him in the end, to the higheſt Commands, than the favour of his Maſter. How he warr'd, the Jews can tell, to whom was more terrible the ſweet name of <hi>Placidus,</hi> than were at other times the Chariots of <hi>Pharaoh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As ſoon as the Wars were at an end, <hi>Placidus</hi> went to <hi>Rome,</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:46454:11"/>where by his milde nature, his unblemiſhed deportment, but more by his great charity, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leiving all neceſſitous perſons, he made himſelf ſo infinitely fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, and was by all the Empire ſo belov'd, that he made the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticians rule fail, enjoying at once the love of the People, and the favour of the Prince. I might ſpeak ſomething of his inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but let this ſuffice. He was ſuch a man, that albeit an Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del, he got the love of God. His houſe was a very ſafe refuge to all that were unfortunate. Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever was in miſery, and came to him for ſuccour, was certain of releif. Whoſoever wanted counſel, found him his ſureſt Oracle. His counſels were ſo wiſe, that his mouth ſeem'd to be a womb of wiſdome. They were ſo candid and ſincere, that <hi>Salomon</hi> would have call'd them, the ſons of a tongue of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:46454:11"/>choyce ſilver. They were ſo uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and ſo wholſome, that with the Holy Ghoſt we may ſay, The mouth of the juſt is a vein of life.</p>
               <p>His good diſpoſition was tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent through the ſweetneſs of his carriage. Every man knew he was a man, but they who hold intelligence with Heaven, would have taken him for an Angel.</p>
               <p>He carry'd himſelf with a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity that was gracefull, and had nothing of the haughty; neither did his mildneſs ever leſſen his reſpect, or his rigour his love. He had the majeſty, not the pride of his equals. He was like <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> which onely of all Rivers is not ſubject to winde. He had the air of a Souldier, both in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanour and countenance: but his ſweet diſpoſition and mildneſs aſſur'd, he had in his breaſt ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted a Temple to Peace. He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled the propitiatory Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:46454:12"/>was Gold without, and of Olive wood within; as the Wand which <hi>Brutus</hi> preſented in the Temple of <hi>Delphos</hi> to <hi>Apollo,</hi> a Rinde of the Cornel tree, a Soul of pure Gold. In fine, our <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidus</hi> was ſo milde, and ſo juſt, that the Publick would have ſent none but him to receive the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Gods, if ſhe again ſailing on the Seas, had arriv'd on the Roman Coaſt.</p>
               <p>At length he reſolved to marry, perſwaded not onely by the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures enjoy'd in Peace, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fermonts by War, but the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary inclination of man, to have a Conſort for his own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and the good of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe.</p>
               <p>And it ſucceeded well, he e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpouſing <hi>Trajana,</hi> a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman of rare chaſtity; and in her affection and deportment ſo conformable to her Husband, that her Habitation was a School of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:46454:12"/>Muſick, in which, from ſeveral voyces, an excellent harmony reſulted. They lov'd one another, they mutually ſubmitted, and had a reciprocal compaſſion, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem for each other. The huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band beheld with no eyes but his wives, and the wife look'd in no other glaſs but her husband. She conform'd her ſelf ſo naturally to his will and diſpoſition, that both in her minde and actions, as it were in a glaſs, every man ſaw the ſolid image of her husband. A prudent woman (ſayes <hi>Plutarch</hi>) will frame her ſelf by Geometri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal diſcipline to her husbands af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections and nature, as the lines and ſuperficies move not alone, but alwayes with the body, ſo a virtuous woman ſhould move, or be at quiet, will, or not will with her husband, making one ſingle Will of two Underſtandings.</p>
               <p>Of this happy Graff grew two Sprouts, which degenerated in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:46454:13"/>nothing from the antient Stock. Their two little Sons, although young, fairly promis'd to imitate the virtues of <hi>Placidus</hi> and <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jana,</hi> living the followers, and dying the companions of their Parents.</p>
               <p>In the mean time, <hi>Placidus,</hi> ordain'd for great things, was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely weary of the idleneſs of Peace; and becauſe no where better, and more to his genius, he could employ himſelf, than in War, he ſpent in hunting the greateſt part of his time.</p>
               <p>Hunting reſembles a War; but reſembles it ſo naturally, that 'tis no abſurdity to ſay, War is a Hunting, and Hunting a War. Does't not happen frequently in a Battail, that the Enemy flyes? in Hunting, that a Beaſt makes reſiſtance? Becauſe they that run away in a time of War are not Beaſts, ſhall not therefore War be a Hunting? Becauſe all that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:46454:13"/>in Hunting make reſiſtance, are not Men, ſhall not therefore Hunting be a War? But be it what it will, our gallant Cavalier ſtill employ'd, and diverted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in hunting, where his labour, his ſtratagems, and the combats he had, (though they never pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd glorious Victories) ſtill exercis'd his body, many times his judgement, and ſometimes his courage; and though ſometimes they were dangerous to him, and ſometimes painfull, yet alwayes they ſerved to entertain and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light him.</p>
               <p>His Huntſman once telling him, he had found at feed a little way off, a great Herd of Stags, he joyfully, (and he could not but be joyfull, if our ſoul ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining ſome ſparks of the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, from which it proceeds, preſages good luck) rang'd the Hunters into order, diſtributed the Dogs, had freſh Horſes at hand,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:46454:14"/>and ſending to watch the leaps, ſo contriv'd his deſign, that the hunting might prove as ſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, as he hop'd 'twould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull, in reſpect of the game.</p>
               <p>O loving God, by how many, and what wayes, contriv'ſt thou the ſalvation of the ſenſeleſs ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner? The Wood hath no retreat in all its dreadfull horrours, and ſecret lurking holes, where the ſoul may ſo lye hid, as God doth not ſeek it, to beſeech it to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of him Graces, Mercies, Heaven, and Divinity.</p>
               <p>In the morning, by break of the day, which was to ſhew the Sun of Mercies to a Hunter, <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidus</hi> well furniſh'd with Men and Horſes, rode towards the fore mentioned Forreſt; where no ſooner they arriv'd, but diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd the Herd they ſought. Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one there fingling out his game, began to purſue the flying Deer, to ſee who could bear away the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:46454:14"/>Prize; which while they endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd, a Hart ſo great, and breath'd, fell to <hi>Placidus</hi> his ſhare, that it led him amain into ſo uncouth and remote a place, that (his Horſe now beginning to fail him) he was hopeleſs of the Prey he had promis'd ſo fairly to himſelf. <hi>Placidus</hi> loſing the Deer, rode ſadly away; but when he was under a cliff, and caſually lifted up his head, he ſpy'd again the Stag, who (leaping ov'r the top of the rock, with his head ſpreading out with knotty beams, and at bay, being turned towards him, as if he ſtaid there to devour him) ſtood proudly expecting him.</p>
               <p>The Stag (as Saint <hi>Jerome</hi> and Saint <hi>Baſil</hi> write) draws the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents by panting out of caves, &amp; deſtroyes them. 'Twas the work of a Deity to ſend a Stag to purify his breaſt, which had been a cave to harbour the Serpent of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:46454:15"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Placidus</hi> (greatly terrify'd at the ſtratagems of the fact, and not a little amaz'd) ſtood muſing what to do; but it ſeeming ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd to give the weary Beaſt any time to take breath, leap'd haſtily to the ground, making ſure of his game, if he could gain the top of the cliff.</p>
               <p>He had ſcarce begun to go on, but he heard a voyce thunder in his ear, which though weak and ſad, carry'd with it, I know not what of horrour, which diſorder'd all the blood in his breaſt, where his troubled ſpirits ſtrayed out of the way, to meet in the heart.</p>
               <p>Caſting about his eyes to finde from whence the voyce came, he diſcover'd (O ſight never to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired enough) betwixt the horns of the Hart, a Chriſt crucify'd, who bath'd with tears, and full of brightneſs, beheld him with ſuch tenderneſs, that perhaps he might have dy'd of delight, if
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:46454:15"/>the confuſion of hearing himſelf guilty had not qualify'd it. <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidus,</hi> ah dear <hi>Placidus,</hi> why per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuteſt thou me? What have I done unto thee? So Chriſt, who deſcended from Heaven into the Woods, to make a Sinner a Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phin, renewed his inſtance, weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more than ever, and full of love and zeal for his ſalvation.</p>
               <p>O Lord, ay me, O Lord, no more leſt I dye; no more, O ſweetneſs, O ſorrow, whatſoever it be, I feel the Hart that ſtrikes me to the heart. Behold me pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate at thy feet, wholly peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and all thine. Diſpoſe of me as thou pleaſeſt. But who, who art thou Lord, that ſo gently reprehend'ſt me? So <hi>Placidus,</hi> who dazled with a heavenly ray of Chriſts brightneſs, had been comforted in a moment, illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated, and enflam'd, languiſhing and lying on the ground, fell into an amorous extaſy.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:46454:16"/>
               <p>Who am I, dear <hi>Placidus?</hi> who am I? Does not the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs thou taſteſt witneſs it? Does not the exceſs of my charity teach thee? Does not the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe of thy conſcience ſpeak me to thee? Ah, who am I? I am Jeſus Chriſt, who created thee, redeem'd thee, and will ſave thee, if thou obey me. I am that God, who deſcending from the Throne of my Glory, dear <hi>Placidus,</hi> for thy ſake have veſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my Deity with fleſh, it ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too little for my love to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute no more to thy ſalvation than that pure act of my will, which alone was ſufficient to ſave thee. I deſire thou ſhould'ſt ſee, that for thy ſake I us'd all occaſions to ſuffer my ſelf wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly to be trampled on, and torn in pieces.</p>
               <p>Ask but theſe veins, theſe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, theſe bowels, and they'll tell thee, whether I have in them
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:46454:16"/>all one ſingle drop of moyſture to keep me alive; what I could not ſpill, I have vented by ſweat; what I could not ſweat, I have caus'd to be drawn out by lances from my heart. And thou <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidus,</hi> what doſt thou for me? what doſt thou for thy ſelf?</p>
               <p>So anſwered the Father of Mercies, when <hi>Placidus</hi> began to cry out, No more, my God, no more Graces, this plenty is too great, a breaſt of fleſh cannot hold a whole Paradiſe. Ah me, wilt thou bury Beatitude in a vaſe of Perdition, my dear and ſweet God, now indeed that I know thee? But how canſt thou endure, and much more love, ſo wicked a Creature? Why doſt not unnail thoſe hands, and pierce this breaſt, which is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to harbour ſo ingrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, wicked, and rebellious a ſoul?</p>
               <p>Then weeping abundantly,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:46454:17"/>like a devout Penitent, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed himſelf in the fire of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, God Almighty giving him an eſſay of the unſpeakable and incomprehenſible ſweetneſs of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal felicity.</p>
               <p>Riſe <hi>Placidus,</hi> go hence to the City, and there with thy Wife and children, have recourſe to my Prieſt, and be baptized: then coming back hither, thou ſhalt here enjoy my preſence; where unveiling to thee the deep my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of my faith, and telling thee ſome particulars of thy fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture condition, I will again diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs thee with comfort and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude.</p>
               <p>So ſpeaking, vaniſh'd our moſt mercifull Father, who, rather upon a Croſs, than the ſhoulders of Seraphins, would appear unto him, to let the World know, that when the ſalvation of a Sinner is in queſtion, if the Jews will not crucifie him, he will again crucify himſelf.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:46454:17"/>
               <p>Here the new Chriſtian much amaz'd, yet full of confidence and love, was about to complain of God, that he had ſo ſoon taken from his ſight ſo ſweet an object. But he was reprehended by that light, which had more illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his minde, than beatified his eyes. Ah no (ſaid he, having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collected himſelf) I will not take it ill, no my God. If I had ſtill enjoy'd thy ſweet preſence, I ſhould have loſt that happy time which I owe to the obedience of thy Commandments. My God; thy moſt holy will be done, I go hence, my dear God. Be pleas'd to give me ſtrength and conſtancy to ſerve thee, in order to the will and zeal thou haſt given me to deſire it.</p>
               <p>Speaking thus, and burning with zeal for the ſervice of God, he was even ready to creep on his hands and feet to <hi>Rome,</hi> in the poſture he then found himſelf.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:46454:18"/>Every thing tends to its center in the moſt direct line. <hi>Placidus</hi> had already left all his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in the track of his will, and would out-run himſelf, to ſhew his prompt obedience to his God.</p>
               <p>This zeal made him think of his Horſe, whoſe natural ſwift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs might carry him with more ſpeed to his Baptiſm. Then leap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the ſaddle, and ſpurring him on, he poſted towards <hi>Rome.</hi> His earneſt deſire of getting thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, made him impatient of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay. The memory of the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures he had newly enjoyed, tranſported him, and his wiſhes, to get out of the dangerous ſtate of Paganiſm, were a torment to him. O how many times, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collecting himſelf, did he ſay, Let's moderate this pleaſure, my ſoul, let's look to our ſelves, leſt the Horſe by going out of the way with his errours, prolong
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:46454:18"/>ours. O let's go hence, let's make haſt away, God will direct us. O dear, O ſweet, and loving God, and when deſerv'd I ever theſe favours? and how at any time was I worthy of them, who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, and in all things, and in every place, have been voyd of all juſtice, and full of all iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? Ah dear Wife, what wilt thou ſay, when I ſhall inform thee of the favours God does us? what wilt thou ſay? will thy boſome contain them? canſt thou reſiſt this ſweetneſs, and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive comfort, and be fortified by the rayes, which out of compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, moſt loving and moſt merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full God, and God too late known, I have beheld and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted.</p>
               <p>With theſe, or the like medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, the Chriſtian <hi>Actaeon</hi> (having ſeen in the Woods the <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ana</hi> of Chriſts Humanity, Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to the Sun of Divinity) rode
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:46454:19"/>along, ſometimes feeling his heart torn by the barking and biting remembrance of his former of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences; and at other times, find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf a new man, flew with his ſoul to the feet of Chriſt, as the Hart to the fountains of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, with as much thirſt as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence.</p>
               <p>Being come at laſt to the City, lighting off his Horſe, and going up to his Wife (who flying, came to meet him with her extended arms) he began. What wilt thou ſay, my dear Wife, when thou ſhalt underſtand the news I bring? When <hi>Trajana,</hi> weeping through abundance of affection, reply'd; I have great things to tell thee, O Husband come too late, and too long expected.</p>
               <p>Having received one another with mutual embraces, and the kindneſs us'd by perſons, who loved each other according to their merit, and reciprocal obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:46454:19"/>
                  <hi>Placidus</hi> (having ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in his eyes which look'd like amazement, and reſembled a trance) rid himſelf of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants officiouſneſs, who employ'd about the ſervice of his perſon, depriv'd him of his liberty; and departing with his dear <hi>Trajana,</hi> to impart unto her the wonders he had ſeen, gave his Wife op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to prevent him in this manner.</p>
               <p>And where haſt thou been ſo great a while, my dear <hi>Placidus?</hi> What toylſome occaſion returns thee to me ſo diſorder'd and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled? What ſad thoughts have ſunk thy eyes? At the time I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to enjoy with thee thoſe eternal felicities, which even the laſt night were promis'd me by a Crucified Man, who was cloathed with the Sun. Why doſt thou meet me ſo ſad, and ſo penſive?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Placidus,</hi> at the name of Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cify'd, (a voyce more pleaſing,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:46454:20"/>becauſe little expected) was all on fire; and lifting up his hands to Heaven, with floods of tears falling from his eyes, brake out in this manner.</p>
               <p>Ah good God! what! every where graces? every where gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces? Go on chearfully, dear Wife, for we have a bountifull God, who is all hands, a God whoſe torn boſome is repleniſhed with graces, a God all honey to comfort us, and all fire to warm us. Thou haſt ſeen our God, dear Wife, thou haſt ſeen our ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. I was not in trouble, but an extaſy of pleaſure. The heat that breaks out at mine eyes, my breaſt was not able to contain. Glory be to God, my dear Wife, that God will be with us; praiſed be God, my dear Wife, that the God of all truth ſeeks us for himſelf. Then as well as his tears would permit him, <hi>Placidus</hi> informed his Wife of the wonders he had
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:46454:20"/>ſeen in the Wood; in the rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of which, how often theſe ſouls were tranſported, with how many extaſies, and how often with a melting affection they now comforted, now commiſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted one another, good Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare you, who occaſion'd it; I, for my part, can eaſier deſire than deſcribe theſe delights. I know <hi>Trajana</hi> (call'd by the Holy Ghoſt, whom we never more worthily anſwer, than when we quickly anſwer) haſtned her <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidus,</hi> Up quickly, let's away, let's readily conſent to ſo many graces; let the jealouſy of loſing them be our rule how to love them.</p>
               <p>O expreſſions, that deſerve to be ſung on the Harp of a Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phin, in the hearing of a Deity.</p>
               <p>All the Curtains of night be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing drawn, as if it meant like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to contribute to the ſalvation of this fortunate Couple, ſecuring
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:46454:21"/>them under its Mantle, from the injuries, or at leaſt the impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments might riſe againſt their good, but then ſharply condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed reſolution, taking with them their two little Sons, and two Servants, whom they long had found faithfull and affectionate, they went to the ſacred Font, to be baptized.</p>
               <p>A good religious man, called <hi>John,</hi> was chief in <hi>Rome</hi> over the Sacramental Treaſury of the growing Church. He (hearing and admiring the deſire, but much more the vocation of the new Believers, and giving God the praiſes, which a Paſtor ſhould do, who ſaw his Flock every day en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe) ſought, I'le not ſay to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm them, for he knew by their zeal, the Holy Ghoſt aſſiſted them, but to ſhew them with what love and pleaſure he reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the favours God their Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor had ſo gratiouſly conferr'd
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:46454:21"/>upon them. The humility with which they approached to the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Font, together with the tears they let fall, in witneſs of the comfort they receiv'd, and the love they expreſſed in their gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude to God, were ſuch as might become two Souls, that had ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken face to face with a living and loving Deity.</p>
               <p>To him that underſtands theſe Love-extaſies, the Writer is not uſefull; and to him that is not capable of them, he is too ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous. Yet I'le not omit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that God ſhowr'd abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly his graces on them, and the treaſures overflowing their ſouls, were ſufficient to enrich, and beatifie the beſt of men.</p>
               <p>The good Prieſt melting in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, was toucht with a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and ſpiritual emulation; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps deſiring more to be their Companion, than rejoycing in the title of Father. They thank'd
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:46454:22"/>him for his charity, and he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended himſelf to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion. They beſought him, (knowing the ill life they had lead) to pray to God for them, that he would be pleas'd to make them new Creatures; and he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated them to ſue for his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, ſince having been ſo antient a Servant in Gods Houſe, he could learn of Children (yet Babes in the ſtate of grace) devotion and wiſdome. He lamented his own coldneſs, and they much rejoyc'd they were come into Gods Houſe, where every thing was fervour. In fine, they here conteſted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout charity, humility, and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. His was the Victory that loſt, and God at the ſame time was the Cauſe of it, the Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, Judge, and Recompence.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euſtachius</hi> and <hi>Theopiſta,</hi> (who had left in the ſacred Font of Baptiſm the names, as well as the belief of <hi>Placidus</hi> and <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jana</hi>)
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:46454:22"/>at laſt took leave of the Prieſt. They parting thence, and returning homeward full of unſpeakable conſolation, went kiſſing their Chiildren; as if they had but newly brought them into the World. O bowels of our bowels (ſaid they) how much are we indebted to God, who even at this time hath beſtow'd you on us? Ah! wretches that we are, how long have we kept you, hanging by the ſmall thread of ſo brittle a life, o're the infernal pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipice of a gulph of mortal eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity! Ah! blind that we are, who loved you ſo little! How happy are ye, who being yet innocent, and regenerated by your God, may no ſooner uſe your reaſon, but begin to do good! Would we had been-ſo fortunate, who obdurate ſo often, and ſo long, have not onely liv'd in ſin, but frequently to ſin; Courage, dear VVife, ſaid the Husband; Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:46454:23"/>dear Husband, ſaid the Wife, ſince God in his infinite mercy hath pardon'd us; let's think now at laſt, how to make our ſelves worthy of the pardon we have had, and operate in that manner, our God repent not he hath pardon'd us. So ſpeaking to themſelves, by the virtue of the charity of God, which poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſing a breaſt, turns it all into heart, they reſolved not to yield even to the Seraphins them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, in loving ſo bountifull a God. But what ſaid I of Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phins? Not to yield to God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, in loving God.</p>
               <p>He will love (ſaid they) more than we; for being all know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and all goodneſs, he can have correſpondence with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and condignly love himſelf: but he ſhall not ſurpaſs us in love, in what we are able, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we will love him with our will; we'll onely deſire him,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:46454:23"/>onely covet him, and onely ſeek him. We'll do ſo dear Wife, we'll do ſo dear Husband; and let us declare our reſolution to God, that he may be pleas'd to further our deſire.</p>
               <p>With theſe, or the like paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, they came home, where <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtachius</hi> (repairing the forces of his body with meat, and recover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf of the wearineſs cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by his pains in the VVood, and the reſtleſs agitation of his minde, after he had order'd a new hunting the day following) fell aſleep: how he reſted, you may gueſs, if you know how one reſts who lyes down full of ſerious thoughts. His ſleeping was a watching, he contemplated, ſlept not, ſince the meat in his ſtomack could not ſend up fumes to cloud and darken his minde, in which the eternal Sun of the Cherubins did ſhine.</p>
               <p>O how happy are they that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:46454:24"/>are capable of this happineſs? A good man is a Tabernacle of the grace, and a Theater of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God. Every thing he doth, hath contentment joyn'd to it. He neither eats, drinks, nor ſleeps, but with this conſolation, that God ſeaſons everything to him. What wonder is it then, that loathing theſe things of the world, he ſometimes leads a life, which fools call Madneſs? Theſe, theſe are the ſouls God loves to converſe with: with theſe, as with ſome rare work of his hands, he is ſo well pleas'd, that he hath at other times declar'd by word of mouth, to love them as his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, as his Children, and things made according to the rule and contentment of his heart. And is not man mad, if (while he lives here upon Earth, and may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with God) he neglect it? O fools if we know it not, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate men if we know it!</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:46454:24"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euſtachius</hi> roſe early in the morning; Mad man! what ſaid I? at midnight; and before his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy eyes had ſatisfied the neceſſity of nature, the enamour'd <hi>Euſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius</hi> left ſleeping, and ſuddenly leaping out of his bed, God grant, ſaid he, with a heart full of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, that I have not ſlept too long. He goes ſollicitous to the window, to ſpy out the morning, but finds, that the night hath not run yet half its courſe. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſatisfied that he had not ſlept too long, he was ſtill im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient, as unable to ſuſtain an expectation, which was very painfull, by the violence of ſo earneſt and amorous a deſire. He ſuppoſed <hi>Aurora</hi> had wrong'd him, in ſuſpending ſo long the coming of that Sun which was to conduct him to the feet of the Sun of Juſtice. He thought to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to his bed, to have ſlept out the remainder of the night, but his
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:46454:25"/>zeal perſwaded him it was ſacr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to referr to the arbitrement of ſleep, a Viſion that deſerv'd to be long'd for with impatience by the Angels themſelves. He would have been glad that ſleep had overcome him, to reſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out offence, and paſs away the time, which he knew not how to know without paſſion. He would have been waking, though it had been with pain, if he could have onely thought on what he ſhould do when his God ſhould appear: but the more he thought on it, the more he perceived his deſire and longing to be there, was aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented in his heart.</p>
               <p>In theſe ſweet afflictions, <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtachius</hi> enjoyed the time he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to ſpend; and while he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected this long'd for Viſion, he prepared himſelf ſo, as not to be made expect any longer, the other he deſir'd and ſigh'd for in a high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er degree.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:46454:25"/>
               <p>At break of day, having di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed in fit places his Dogs and Huntſmen, (arm'd with the breaſtplate of faith) he rode ſolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citous towards the VVood; there to arrive, and ſeparate himſelf from the company, as a Fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, was the thing he intended. The center of his heart, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reer, was the Paradiſe of the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, where he thought to finde his Chriſt. The horrour accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying ſolitude, increaſed amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and terrour in his heart, while he ſtay'd for that Divinity, whoſe coming every moment he attended. Each whiſtling of the air, and noyſe of the leaves, he reverently ſuppoſed were the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, ſinging praiſes to that Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, whoſe ſacred preſence repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented the VVood, as a Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to him.</p>
               <p>Being come to the cliff, where at firſt he ſaw his Chriſt; and lighting off his Horſe, with a
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:46454:26"/>breaſt full of reverence, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated himſelf to adore that Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, whoſe Viſion he atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, with no leſs fear than con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence. A Light, like that of Paradiſe, brake out of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of a little cloud, and <hi>Euſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius</hi> was again made partaker of the preſence of Chriſt, who ſpake in this manner.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euſtachius,</hi> thou haſt begun well, perſevere; for if thou hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt on to the end, thou wilt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance my ſervice, and ſave thy own ſoul. The favours I have done thee, will be envy'd by Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, whoſe temptations, if thou ſhalt reſiſt valiantly, thou ſhalt overcome gloriouſly. I my ſelf, for thy good, will permit him to aſſault thee; reſiſt, and be victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious. I will be ſure to help thee, do not waver in thy faith. Thy honours, thy children, thy wife, and thy riches, I have given thee; and 'tis neceſſary thou make it
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:46454:26"/>appear of whom thou doſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge them, and with what affection; Thy faith and thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy muſt aſſure me of thy love. I have reſolved to try, how much of thy heart thou art willing to give me in thy love, who have, to ſave thee, ſpilt my blood and life.</p>
               <p>What may we, O Chriſtians, believe he reply'd, whoſe perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons we may meaſure by the love of God to him. I ſpeak not of the love by which God comply'd with his perfections, I mean the love by which he made him perfect. I imagine he anſwered thus: And why ſhould'ſt thou give me ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant a knowledge of thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, moſt amiable God, but to love thee, and in order to the tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I muſt ſuffer? And what ſort of tribulation (able to balance the infinite love I ow thee, and thou doſt deſerve) can a body of durt, more brittle than glaſs, be able to ſupport? If thou wilt beſtow
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:46454:27"/>a love upon me, proportionable to my ſufferings, employ, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, all thy power, in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting and deviſing an afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as great as the love I bear thee, as the love I beg of thee. But this is not enough, O love of my love, this is not enough, 'tis neceſſary thou give me a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which encountring all theſe evils, will not cry before 'tis hurt. Thou call'ſt me to affliction, and I run to affliction. And what can I ever endure, that may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piate ſuch a multitude of ſins, much leſs return ſo many favours? And what tribulation can at any time be diſpleaſing to me, if ſo ſweet and ſo beloved a God, a God of conſolation and comfort, will aſſiſt me? If I have with me, or rather within me, the vigour, health, and life of all things, what evill will be able to hurt me? what grief make me grieve? If I muſt do thee ſervice
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:46454:27"/>with affliction, I would be affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted when I am not in thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; for I cannot e're imagine, how that he that ſerves thee, can ſuffer affliction. And how wilt thou value the afflictions, which e're they torment, thou aſſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt? Grant, O my God, grant I conjure thee, by the merits of that infinite love with which thou lov'ſt thy ſelf, grant I may love thee as well as I deſire, and grant I may deſire it as much as thou deſerv'ſt it, and then come Hell, and let Men arm themſelves together with the Angels, and joyn with thee in putting me to torment, I ſhall not at all value them. I love a God, too ſweet, too dear, and too loving. VVhen he ſhould caſt Thunderbolts at me, he comes with his nail'd hands to comfort me. VVhen he will have me ſuffer, he comes to tell me of it, to animate and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage me. And for ſuch a God
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:46454:28"/>can I ſuffer? I may, but I do more deſire, than believe it. I believe it, becauſe he tells me ſo; but I doubt he will not tell it me, to make me pleaſe him by conſenting to it; and I would by ſuffering do ſomething that might pleaſe ſo bountifull a God.</p>
               <p>With theſe, or affections of this kinde, he overflow'd, who in the eyes of Chriſt learnt the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Divinity that is practis'd in Loves School.</p>
               <p>The more ſcorching and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flam'd the Earth returns the Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beams to the Sun, the more vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly the Sun both waters and makes fruitfull the Earth. God is as the Sun to our ſoul, the more fervently we return him our love, the more vigorous he is in the heat of his love to Mankinde. They ſeem to ſcorch, yet make the ſoul fruitfull; which the more it is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flam'd, the more it prevaileth with God, for the oil of his heavenly grace.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:46454:28"/>
               <p>So affectionately anſwer'd <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtachius;</hi> but Chriſt more affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionately reply'd: Theſe replyes I ſhould proſecute, but how to comprehend and expreſs them, though I wanted not the force of underſtanding, I ſhold want with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt the perfection of virtue.</p>
               <p>Gods conceptions onely charity underſtands, and not reaſon. To deſcribe them, ſerves only to deſire them, and not to make us fit to comprehend them. God only makes us capable of them; and he that underſtands them, underſtands the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by grace &amp; not by ſpeculation.</p>
               <p>What Chriſt did communicate to <hi>Euſtachius,</hi> ſure was moſt true, and I wiſh we were worthy to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of the tendernes of the love he expreſſed to him. He ſhew'd him how well he was pleas'd with the zeal of his good will, &amp; inſtructed him in the moſt hidden mſteries of his faith. He encourag'd &amp; fortify'd him againſt the fierce temptations
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:46454:29"/>of the Devil, and after very many revelations, (which would have been favours in Paradiſe it ſelf) he promis'd to haſten his Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Crown.</p>
               <p>VVhen the Viſion was ended, (in the period of which, the faſter Chriſt vaniſh'd out of ſight, the more he ador'd him in his heart) <hi>Euſtachius,</hi> full of inward conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, (having kiſſed the ſtones, ſaluted the trees, and reverenc'd the place, which had been the Altar, the VVitneſs, and Temple of his happineſs) rode again to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the City.</p>
               <p>Being come to his VVife, who expected him with the anxious ſolicitude, which is not without hope, while he imparted to her the contents of the paſt revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Holy Ghoſt communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to her its conſolations and ſweetneſs; as if he ſhould ſay, 'Tis juſtice thou ſhould'ſt ſhare in the delights of the Viſion, as
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:46454:29"/>thou art to ſhare in the torments and afflictions mention'd in it.</p>
               <p>The ſharp temptations threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, rais'd no fear in this VVo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, who onely was effeminate in the duties of a Mother.</p>
               <p>Ah, God fights not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer; and what glory can a Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty have in the ruine of a VVorm? The ſtronger his aſſaults be, the willinger he loſes, and with grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter glory. Gods trials are accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with his Graces, and his Crucible makes the Gold, tryes it not. Let's comfort our ſelves, dear Husband, let's comfort our ſelves; he will loſe if we loſe; and what can we loſe, who have quitted the propriety of our ſelves? And what will God try in us, if we be ſtrong? That cannot by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture be ſtrong, which is naturally weak. If he will have us ſtrong, we ſhall not be weak; we ſhall be ſtrong enough, if we be his, yes, yes, his, let's wholly be his;
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:46454:30"/>and we ſhall be ſo alwayes, and better Voluntiers, becauſe we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire it, than becauſe we are ſo na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally; and neither the force of oppoſition, nor the rage of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation, or the terrour or pain of death, ſhall ever have the power to make us not his. And now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his in this manner, ſhall we not be defended by ſo gratious a God, who when we were his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, and rebels, protected us?</p>
               <p>So ſaid <hi>Theopiſta,</hi> in whom the grace of God ſpake more than her tongue; for 'twas that which inform'd her how ſuch things were to be known and deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
               <p>But having preſcribed new laws to their affections, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulated their ſenſes, they ſtudy'd that virtue which accuſtomes men to goodneſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euſtachius</hi> thought himſelf ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to reform, in the firſt place,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:46454:30"/>his Houſe, as he had done his Soul, and in a ſhort time re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd it to that ſtate of perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that knowing what was needleſs, he quickly began to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the tranquillity, which men by living out of neceſſity, aim at. Humility chas'd out of his Houſe the pride of ſuch Furniture, as makes the Maſter of it the moſt inconſiderable thing there. His Table did nouriſh, not nauſeate; for he fed not to ſtir up an appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite, but to ſatiate hunger. His Cloaths did cover, not adorn him; for the habit is too gaudy, which deſerves more reſpect than the man. His Walls were not beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified with <hi>Mercury</hi>'s Thefts, the Adulteries of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> and the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famies of <hi>Venus.</hi> And how can the Soul be held good, whoſe Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy's not thought happy, if even the Walls themſelves, which ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure its repoſe, be not wicked?
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:46454:31"/>If even the bowls he drinks in, afford not more laſciviouſneſs to gaze on, than wine to pleaſe his palate? He was waited on, not idolized, by his Slaves; and his Cup-bearer, by his ſerving him on the knee, feign'd not to believe he was a <hi>Jupiter.</hi> Whoſoever nam'd him, did not ſwear with a preface of radiant titles, he ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd him transform'd into a Star. He receiv'd not into his Houſe that kinde of mad men, called Dancers, (People, all whoſe learning's in their feet, all whoſe meaſure's in their errours) for there was no Feaſt, but that of a good Conſcience; neither <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheus, Amphion,</hi> or <hi>Circe,</hi> had any thing to do there; their har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony was the ſighs, with which, from the remembrance of their former tranſgreſſions, they paſs'd to the hopes of a future felicity. There was no diſcord, they two
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:46454:31"/>agreeing to ſing perpetually the mercies of ſo gratious, and ſo bountifull a God. No revellings were heard there, nor tumults caus'd by Playes. Nor us'd they there Dice, which while with golden promiſes they ſeem to flatter men, do cheat them of their lively hood, and diſhonour their death.</p>
               <p>In his Houſe they look'd after the manuring of the Soul, not the Garden, where Charity flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, Piety, and Devotion, and not the Anemone of <hi>Theſſaly,</hi> the Musk-flower of <hi>Greece,</hi> and Granadiglia of <hi>Mexico.</hi> Good God, how is't poſſible the intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance of man ſhould be ſo great, as (to pleaſe his ſenſe of ſmelling) to bring fading flowers from the famouſeſt and remoteſt Eaſtern Provinces?</p>
               <p>And who would e're believe it, that the luxury of a prince (why
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:46454:32"/>ſpeak I of a Prince, of a Citizen, and often too neceſſitous) had caus'd a frail Flower to be brought at his infinite charge o're the Oce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, through Deſarts, and o're Mountains, into a new World, and onely for perfuming the Air for an unfortunate man, who in a whole Hemiſphear can finde no ſmell to pleaſe him? He that will venture all his fortune in a Flower-pot of earth, deſerves to be ruin'd by each blaſt of winde.</p>
               <p>Now the example of <hi>Euſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius</hi> and his Wife, had corrected in that manner, and reform'd all the reſt of the Family, that even out of reverence they forbore to do ill.</p>
               <p>His Slaves were rather Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars than Servants, who lov'd their Maſter out of wonder, not onely out of gratitude, and were us'd like Children, not Enemies. Authority without contempt, Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:46454:32"/>without avarice, Honour without ambition, and Splendour without luxury, remain'd within his Walls. In fine, his Houſe was become a Pantheon, where Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, Temperance, Charity, and each other Heavenly Virtue, were held in great reverence. If a Chriſtian had deſir'd to behold the two Tables of ſtone, where God with his own finger had written and engraven the Precepts of his Law, he could no where finde them better, than in the hearts of <hi>Euſtachius</hi> and <hi>Theopiſta.</hi> Each of them was mark'd, as the Plate of Gold on the Miter of <hi>Aaron,</hi> with <hi>Holineſs to the Lord.</hi> They were in that degree of perfection, that I cannot deſcribe it; the Touch-ſtone will tell it: but God muſt touch them, to tell us their worth. And what will that be?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="book">
               <pb facs="tcp:46454:33"/>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:46454:33"/>
               <head>The Loving Husband, and Prudent Wife, &amp;c.</head>
               <head>The ſecond Book.</head>
               <p>WE have ſeen already how this valiant Champion was reform'd by the Sovereign Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander of the Chriſtian Militia: I muſt now relate the actions he couragiouſly perform'd with his Pike in his hand, on the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſeſt Frontiers of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.</p>
               <p>He loſt in the firſt charge, all the lives of his ſlaves, occaſion'd
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:46454:34"/>by a violent and contagious di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe, for which there was no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy. All attempts for their health were in vain; and while ſome endeavour'd to prevent their deſtruction, and others ſearch'd after the cauſe of the malady, they were by its effects deſtroy'd and conſum'd themſelves: the ſpectacle of which was ſo horrid and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, that the death of the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician was often lamented by the languiſhing Patient.</p>
               <p>Solitude inherited his Houſe, which his Friends, afraid of death, retreated from, to avoyd the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, whoſe Violence made Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick of no uſe, while it gave them no time to conſult what to do.</p>
               <p>What ſorrow this loſs might oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to <hi>Euſtachius,</hi> and how vaſt a ſufferer he was, he can beſt tell, that knows how great a part of the greatnes and riches of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes, the Slaves were.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:46454:34"/>
               <p>They ſow'd, plow'd, and reap'd. The Yeoman of the Celler, the Barber, Tayler, Groom of the Stable, and often too the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter-man, were all Slaves. They waited in the Chamber and Hall, and were Sewers and Cup-bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. A Citizen had of them on the rental of his revenue, to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of a thouſand; and <hi>Seneca</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, that that Age had built Houſes like Cities for greatneſs, and had Families equal to Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in number.</p>
               <p>Fleſh and Blood ſo gall'd in its intereſt, made <hi>Euſtachius</hi> ſenſible, that he could not without infinite grief bear ſo notable a loſs.</p>
               <p>Of what uſe will the Ground be without a Tiller? Cattle with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Cow-herd? Houſes without a Houſe-keeper? and Lords without Servants? In one onely day, with a ſingle and a momentary diſaſter, as it were, lyes ſo languiſhing,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:46454:35"/>and diſcomfited, all the fortune of his Houſe? And whither ſhall he run to repair it? Perhaps to Chriſt, who no ſooner was known and adored, but blaſted and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed all his Goods. Could he have fared worſe, if he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to adore him? Is this the encouraging of his Servants? This a way to comfort and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm them? Ah poor <hi>Euſtachius,</hi> what wilt thou do? What hopes haſt thou left in the progreſs of thy faith, the firſt entrance into which hath loſt thee all thou hadſt? To abandon a <hi>Jupiter,</hi> who made thee gliſter every where like the Sun, to follow a Chriſt, who can onely give thee nakedneſs? Thou never would'ſt credit this truth, till thou hadſt felt the ſmart of thy errour. Thou too eaſily haſt believed this God, and what God is this that will never ſuffer thee to be happy, but
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:46454:35"/>when thou art his Enemy; nor makes thee unfortunate, but when thou art his Friend? Ah Wretch! return to thy ſelf, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn.</p>
               <p>So Satan ſuggeſted to <hi>Euſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius,</hi> in whom the piercing ſenſe of his ſudden calamity could not chooſe but raiſe a ſtorm of affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Fools are inſenſible of diſaſters, but wiſe men bear them valiantly. Nature will have us to reſent them, but Reaſon to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage them. Virtue may reſtrain our reſentment of unhappineſs, but cannot ſo ſubdue it, but it na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally will rebel. Valour would decay, if it were not kept in acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. We are born to fight thus, and remunerated for ſo doing. God after the Creation would have plac'd us at firſt among the Angels, if he had not been wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling we ſhould fight for the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory our activity aſpires to. We
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:46454:36"/>might have enjoy'd without op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition the glory of delight, but not of repoſe and reward.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euſtachius</hi> (toſs'd up and down, not dejected) acknowledging eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing from Gods hand, did comfort himſelf. 'Tis a favour (he ſaid patiently) that the ſcourge we deſerve for ſo many tranſgreſſions, vents its fury on the ſhoulders of our fortune. Let's think on what remains, ſince that which is paſt is irrevocable. Let's be thankfull to God for what he hath left us, and thank him for what he hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away. Was he not mercifull to us, in ſuffering us to enjoy ſo much time? Who knows, if his depriving us of our Goods, hath not been a greater favour than his giving them to us? How many have loſt their lives, by being Maſters of ſo many deſperate fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows? The name of God be praiſed, we have ſtill ſo much
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:46454:36"/>left us, that living with much leſs, we ſhall live with much more than is neceſſary. Can we part with leſs than the lives of a few Slaves, to have an occaſion of conforming our ſelves to Gods will?</p>
               <p>While he was thus reaſoning with himſelf, behold a panting Meſſenger arriv'd, whoſe wan and ſad face uſher'd in his diſmal news.</p>
               <p>It grieves me, my Lord, ſaid he, to relate what will doubtleſs afflict you. But the loſs is as great, as the tidings inevita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table. All your Flocks of Sheep, your Oxen, and Horſes, are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd by a ſudden contagion, and have left us as poor, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded and amaz'd.</p>
               <p>When God permits the Devil to command, his Scepter is of fire. He ſo fears his authority of deſtroying ſhould be clipt, that
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:46454:37"/>he undermines, eſteeming the time loſt he employes in demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing and battering.</p>
               <p>To be poor on the ſudden, is a great thing with patience to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, eſpecially for him who is not obliged to Fortune, but ows all he hath to his own virtuous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>bours.</p>
               <p>Nothing in this World we love <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore than the fruits of our own labours. We love them, becauſe they are commodious; we love them, becauſe we got them hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and we love them, becauſe they are our Children: but yet for all this, their loſs would be ſupportable, if we lov'd them not as teſtimonies and aſſurances of our virtue.</p>
               <p>For this laſt blow, which ruin'd entirely all the ſubſtance, not onely the greatneſs of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtachius</hi> his Houſe, what may we imagine he ſaid, whoſe onely hope
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:46454:37"/>was, the ſale of his Cattle, or their profits at leaſt, would have repair'd the loſs he had ſuffered by the death of his Slaves.</p>
               <p>He ſaid, Praiſed, bleſſed, and thanked be God, who hath eas'd me of the weight of ſo painfull a care. Whom ſhould I have truſted with the government of this Flock, which onely was left me, after my Serva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts death, to diſquiet and tro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> me? Dear Wife, our God takes from us all impediments, that we being freer, and diſengag'd from all affairs, may attend his ſervice, and be thankfull to him. Be he alwayes glorified, and I beſeech all the Angels, together with all Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, to thank him for me, ſince I cannot perform it of my ſelf. God alone be my patrimony, my treaſure, and ſubſtance; by virtue of him, my loſſes will not hurt me, my gains not diſtract me, not
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:46454:38"/>my miſeries afflict me. If my God be but with me, what thing can I want?</p>
               <p>But what ſhould theſe poor per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons do, I ſhould ſay Lords, if the Peſtilence had not kill'd too this title? By ſelling the beſt furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of their Houſe, and their Lands, which for want of looking too, were wholly out of order, they both patiently ſupported, and conſum'd too their poor Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily. Their Friends quickly left them, ſince 'tis a uſual fault in the world, to fly away from thence, whence Proſperity is departed.</p>
               <p>Many blame Fortune for this, and ſay, ſhe's ſo cruel, ſhe would think ſhe had left him too much; whoſe poverty ſhe hath decreed, if ſhe had not too, depriv'd him of Friends. But wiſe men do know, this fault is our own, and not the Stars. Man is afraid to touch him whoſe condition is
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:46454:38"/>infected, and cannot give us any thing but contagion; or pretend, but to our Goods.</p>
               <p>The not being a good Friend to ones Friend, makes us not count a Friend among our proper Goods; elſe 'twould be impoſſible we ſhould think it a misfortune to part with any thing of our own, for his ſake, whom we valued as one of the pretiouſeſt Jewels we have. His Followers deſerted him, becauſe he wanted means to maintain them; and he that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not live of himſelf, ſtands in need of another. He was not cry'd up, becauſe he was not rich. Accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations and ſplendour go toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and he that is wealthy, may be prudent, wiſe, and vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant. Every man did pity him, but no man aſſiſted him. All knew he was innocently unfortunate, but woe to him whoſe Innocence muſt onely relieve him.</p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:46454:39"/>
               <p>He that could not help him, deſir'd it affectionately; and he that could do it, avoyded meeting with him, for fear of being mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to pity. Men fly from the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, as from the infected with the Plague. And though we all know, what we do is the thing we would not have done to our ſelves, yet intereſt ſo ſwayes us, we had rather deſerve cruelty by our avarice, than purchaſe mercy by compaſſion.</p>
               <p>Having ſpent what they had ſold, theſe Noble Perſons began to be ſenſible of the outrages of ſhame, which alwayes accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and torments us in adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity. He that is unfortunate, thinks every one derides him, objecting his neceſſities as a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment for his offences, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing him of folly in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of his fortune.</p>
               <p>Their Noble Birth likewiſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach'd
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:46454:39"/>them with their preſent low condition. They griev'd to be a diſgrace unto thoſe who had left them ſo well; and though their new Religion had extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh'd all ambition in them, yet they thought it unhandſome to do any thing misbeſeeming No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, (a gift of Heaven) that ſwerves not from its principles, of which, the obligation to uphold it with honour and ſtate, is not the leaſt. In fine, their laſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge was a firm reſolution to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat far from <hi>Rome,</hi> where to be ſeen living in that manner, was the greateſt affliction their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty made them ſuffer. They thought, that going where un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known they could have what was neceſſary, would be a relinquiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the qualities at <hi>Rome,</hi> which made even things of ſuperfluity but neceſſary.</p>
               <p>If to live in the luſter of a
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:46454:40"/>Prince, were as eaſy a thing as to live like an ordinary man, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune would not have many Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars. Solitude and Poverty they ſuppos'd would make them moſt happy.</p>
               <p>O God, with what tranquillity ſhall we enjoy our ſelves in a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred peace, exempt from the noyſe and tumults of Followers, who, by reaſon of their many neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, are continually troubleſome and importunate? O God, with what freedome may we (being at liberty) dive into the contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſervice of that beloy'd Deity, who ſeaſons ſo ſweetly to us our calamities? And when in the greatneſs of the world, and honours of the times, were we ſenſible of the contentment of heart we have now, among ſo many miſeries, which ſhould grieve and afflict us? Now I plainly ſee (ſaid <hi>Euſtachius</hi>) what
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:46454:40"/>terreſtrial riches are; they are burthens and impediments, which load, vex, and weary us. And when ſhall we be in a place, where the opinion of the world will not force us to do homage to unconſtant Fortune?</p>
               <p>Will the Earth ever be ſo bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, as not to afford us even pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digally, nouriſhment? Shall we ever finde any ſo inhumane to envy our condition, and enſnare us? Can we probably want at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance, if ſick, in a place where we ſhall be four in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, of the ſame blood, religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and minde? Can our Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren want Maſters, while we, who have ſpoken with God, ſhall have nothing to do, but to teach them what advantage it is to ſpeak with God.</p>
               <p>And though we ſhould have nothing to help us (reply'd <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſta</hi>)
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:46454:41"/>can we ever do amiſs in that place, whither we go to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the will of God? There, where we may ſatisfie the debt our many ſins have contracted? There, where by our ſuffering, we may return our thanks unto God, for his infinite favours?</p>
               <p>When they had agreed on this, and pack'd up ſome few neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, in the night poorly cloath'd, with bundles on their backs, and leading each a Child by the hand, they abandon'd the City, making towards a certain Sea-Town. Who is able to relate the reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of this departure, in ſo poor an equipage, and never more to ſee that native ſoyl, and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Countrey, where ſo long and ſo happily they had liv'd, and with ſo much reſpect and renown? Peradventure each concealed his grief, not to aggravate his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions affliction, or bluſh'd to diſcover his own.</p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:46454:41"/>
               <p>'Tis true, they left voluntarily their Countrey, they left it too moſt willingly, I confeſs: But who hath not a love for himſelf? And who loves himſelf, that loves not his Countrey? O God, declare it you, who permitted them to feel the piercing ſorrows of diſaſters, to make them reliſh better thoſe delights, which made them ſuffer patiently for your ſake.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theopiſta,</hi> peradventure to chear up her Husband, by ſhewing him her alacrity, went joyfully before him, and apace. <hi>Euſtachius</hi> edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd, or rather aſtoniſh'd at the zeal of his Wife, perpended how happy God had made him in his Spouſe, who alone was equiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent to all other ſublunary for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes.</p>
               <p>And what ſhould I do, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate Man that I am, ſo he ſaid, without her, who in travel
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:46454:42"/>is my comfort, and in proſperity my guide; who, when I am weary, refreſhes me, and guards me when I ſleep? Pardon me, O Lord, I acknowledge my crime of ſo great an ingratitude. Am I likewiſe ſo unthankfull, to go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſad as though I were unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate, when I go with ſo religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a Wife, and two ſuch dutifull Children? O dull heart! O heart of earth! When wilt thou leave theſe earthly thoughts? And what have we loſt? Our Herds? Serv'd they otherwiſe than to fill the Exchequer, which was never yet open'd, but in favour of Pride, Luxury, and Vanity? Our Slaves? And art not thou aſham'd, I will not ſay to grieve thou haſt loſt them, but not to be ſorry thou haſt had the rule over them? Ah cruel man! Ah Tyrant! For a man to diſpoſe of another mans life? And why? By what Law?
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:46454:42"/>O barbarous Scythian, for thy conveniency, muſt a hundred men as good as thy ſelf, and often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times better, to foment thy vices, be obliged to thee, depend upon thee, and be chain'd to thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice? He hath not depriv'd thee of thy Herds, he hath not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priv'd thee of thy Slaves, he one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hath depriv'd thee of the means and occaſions of ill, ingratefull man, and art not thou ſenſible of it? art not glad of it? and art not thou thankfull?</p>
               <p>Theſe Noble Pilgrims had ſcarce left their Countrey, but their Houſe was moſt treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly broken open, and robb'd by certain Rogues; who, though they bear the title of Men, yet live of nothing elſe but the ſpoyl. Theeves (ſtill the Enemies and Betrayers of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, of which they are rather
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:46454:43"/>Moths, than part) entred his Houſe, and ſack'd it of the Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture that remain'd, and was ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a reproach than a monument of their decay'd happineſs.</p>
               <p>In the mean time the day came, which the Romanes us'd gratefully to commemorate for the Conqueſt of the Parthians.</p>
               <p>When the People were aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, the Army in armour, the Theater crown'd, and the Prince on his Throne, nothing was want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but the valiant Commander, the Soul of the Camp, the Heart of the Prince, and right hand and Idol of the Common-wealth, and Empire; brave <hi>Placidus</hi> was abſent, who compleated, not onely was the cauſe of the feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city they ſo gloriouſly remembred. While the People thought the General ſtaid redreſſing ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, the delay onely ſerv'd to prolong the applauſes of publick
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:46454:43"/>conſolation. But as ſoon as the Prince and People underſtood, the juſt, magnanimous, and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant Pilgrim was departed, (to fly from the ſhame his poverty might occaſion) 'tis hard to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late with what a congeal'd force all cheeks loſt their red, all eyes were caſt down, and all tongues turn'd to ſilence. Many curs'd Fortune, and murmur'd againſt Providence. It ſeem'd unſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable, not onely unjuſt, ſo va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorous a man, and ſo good, ſhould not onely be ſubject to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages of Chance, but ſuppreſſed by them. Never any Triumph began with more joy, and ended with more ſorrow. But why name I a Triumph? Here they repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented and bewail'd an unhappy Cataſtrophe of Fortune; and the day that was deſign'd for the joy of the Romanes, for the Victory obtain'd o're the Parthians, ſerv'd
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:46454:44"/>onely to chear up the Parthians for the notable loſs the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes had ſuſtain'd, in the ruine of ſo valiant a Commander and Warrier.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Trajan</hi> (as men uſe to do) eſteeming things more, as they have greater need of them, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented the loſs of ſo power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full a Miniſter. Perhaps he was too, moved at the diſaſter it ſelf; for though great Perſons meaſure every thing with the compaſs of their intereſt, yet Virtue doth not ſuffer them to deny him compaſſion, who hath gain'd it by deſert, and demands it as unhappy. A di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent ſearch after them was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, but the new Chriſtians had too ſecretly convey'd away themſelves, and were far enough off, and ſecure.</p>
               <p>They deſign'd <hi>Egypt</hi> as the end of ſo tedious a peregrination;
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:46454:44"/>and being cloſe purſu'd by their unhappineſs, they thought they were oblig'd to ſeek reparation in that Kingdome, where their Chriſt did truſt himſelf, when he fled away young, and was perſecuted by <hi>Herod,</hi> the worſt of the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarchs of <hi>Judea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After many dayes travel, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with their frequent, and daily wants, and the in juries they receiv'd from certain Robbers, they got to the Sea-coaſt at laſt, depriv'd of every thing, but the hope they had in God.</p>
               <p>They embarqued themſelves, to avoyd the incommodities of ſo tedious a Journey, which afoot to undertake with two ſuch young Children, was too difficult a task.</p>
               <p>The winde blew favourably, and the ſhore they ſoon loſt. The Veſſel ſail'd ſo faſt, that perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually it was before the winde.
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:46454:45"/>All Proſperity ſeem'd to be at the Helm. But they went not much further, e're they ſaw, He puts fondly to Sea, who flyes from Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune. The Sky was ſerene, yet it blew hard enough to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitate them into an Ocean of dangers. The winds (which diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreeing in appearance, conſpir'd to deſtroy the poor Bark) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd in a moment the Sun, turn'd the waves topſy-turvy, and rais'd a ſtorm in the Air. They might look into the Sea, and not caſt down their eyes; for being often bury'd between two deep ſhores of raging billows, they were lower than the waters, and afraid of ſailing down to the bottome. 'Twas dreadfull to hear the ſad noyſe of the ſhrowds, which beaten by the winde, ſeem'd hiſſing to bewail the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancy of the waves, and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery of the Sky. Some of the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:46454:45"/>Paſſengers, by encouraging o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, did labour to deceive their own fears; and others, by hiding their faces, ſaid, they fear'd more the viſage of death, than his ſithe. The Mariners endeavour'd to ſtrike the main-yard, which now would be onely commanded by the winde.</p>
               <p>The Pilot lamented the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity he had loſt o're the helm, which obey'd nothing now, but the tyrannous Sea. To ſee light, they were forced to pray it might lighten, and to fear no thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolts; 'twas enough but to think on the devouring waves. In fine, the hope of landing any where; but in the haven of death, was as bold an undertaking, as to ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to Sea without a Boat.</p>
               <p>Albeit a ſweaty fear congeal'd on the brows of the miſerable Paſſengers, yet every one very earneſtly, in order to their ſeveral
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:46454:46"/>Religions, made vows for his own ſafety. <hi>Theopiſta</hi> (who had never ſeen ſuch horrible ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles on the Land) being af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted, and half dead, lay lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing in her dear Husbands arms. He, who more than once had met Death in the face, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending no otherwiſe the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, than not to be inſenſible of it, ſpake to her in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
               <p>Where is your Courage, which boaſted of ſeeking, not onely of enduring the painfulleſt death we can ſuffer for God? No leaf falls to the ground without his diſtinct and particular permiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who hath a care of it; and ſhall we fools, fear the death he permits, or wickedly go about to avoyd what he appoints? And though theſe waves were deſign'd for our Sepulcher, what death can be leſs grievous than that
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:46454:46"/>overwhelms thee? what happier than that does not part thee from thy Husband and Children? and what more fortunate; than that finds thee devot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d to the will of thy Creatour, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing in his ſervice? Believ'ſt not, that this Veſſel, though ſplit, and weather-beaten, can as well ſerve to carry thee to the ſhore of Beatitude, as to the land of <hi>Egypt?</hi> Ah dear Wife! what fears are theſe? He cannot fear ſo much, that loves not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively himſelf; and he cannot love exceſſively himſelf, that loves his God enough. Go to, go to, <hi>Theopiſta;</hi> if God may be calm'd, prayers, not fears will appeaſe him. And if God will be ſerv'd, ſhall not we be aſham'd to ſerve him ſo faintly, and poorly?</p>
               <p>When the Devil ſaw no bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery could affright, much leſs o're<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:46454:47"/>
                  <hi>Euſtachius,</hi> ſounding a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat to the tempeſts, he cleared the Sky to the eyes of this Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger, who ſtill in his heart had the calm of each ſtorm, and all Heaven's ſerenity.</p>
               <p>When the Tempeſt was over, they ſang, and commemorated the daily mercies of their gratious Preſerver. Onely <hi>Theopiſta</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated not her joy, being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham'd and ſad ſhe had ſhew'd ſo little confidence in ſo kinde and ſo mercifull a God. <hi>Euſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius</hi> comforted her, telling her, that her fears had proceeded from the weakneſs of her ſex, and not a want of courage, and that ſhe would not want opportunities of expreſſing her zeal, which was (for Gods ſake) not onely to conteſt with future diſaſters, but the memory of their happineſſes paſt. In the mean time, they took pleaſure in thinking, in
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:46454:47"/>what tender charity, what inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and calm poverty, and what uncouth and free ſolitude they ſhould leade the reſidue of their lives, and ſpend all their affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and exhauſt all their ſpirits in the ſervice of their ſweet and loving God.</p>
               <p>This their daily meditation made them often in an extaſy of delight. The Heaven ſeem'd to them to go faſter than the Ship, ſo great was their longing to be on the ſhore. All the Paſſengers and Mariners beheld with admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the majeſtick poverty, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcreet affection, and humble no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of this Couple, who, even in their adverſity, were honour'd, and envy'd. Some wonder'd, how perſons ſo qualify'd, were ſo poor; but no body could leave wondring, how perſons ſo poor, could be ſo well qualify'd. Every one was attentive to the words of
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:46454:48"/>
                  <hi>Euſtachius,</hi> whoſe expreſſions had a certain air of greatneſs, which made him reſpected. Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one beheld with compaſſion, and delight, the face of <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſta,</hi> whoſe poverty had not chang'd her noble mean, nor al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd her complexion, the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of which diffus'd a certain ſweetneſs, forcing their eyes (though barbarous) to adore her. None could, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhment, behold, with what readineſs and humility, a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and Conquerour of Armies, ran uncall'd to all the duties and affairs of the Sails, the Oars, and Helm. He muſt have wept hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily, that had ſeen with what cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, humility, and curteſy, this moſt noble of Ladies, aiding all without diſtinction; now help'd to make clean what belonged to the Mariners and Veſſel, now aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted in ſerving them, in dreſſing
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:46454:48"/>their meat, and offices of this kinde, the air of whoſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance had made the Voyage fortunate. Every man, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the Maſter of the Veſſel, ſaid he could not chooſe but envy her Husband for his happineſs in her. And who would not think it an incomparable happineſs, to have ſo diſcreet, ſo provident, and ſo loving a Wife?</p>
               <p>They ſail'd ſome dayes ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperouſly, that they quickly made land. At that happy ſight, <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtachius</hi> and <hi>Theopiſta</hi> (tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported with gladneſs and grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude) kneeling, with their hands rear'd to Heaven, gave thanks un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, who at laſt had brought them ſafe to the ſhore; where they truſted they ſhould finde a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented life, and quiet death.</p>
               <p>The Sea-men were ſcarce come into the road, when the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers grown impatient (as if
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:46454:49"/>they had already touch'd the ſhore) began to ſeek their goods, take leave of the Sailers, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie the Maſter for their paſſage, with money, or merchandiſe of like value. Some bid the Pilot farewell, and others thank'd their Friends for their company, while the Mariners went about, begging ſomething to drink; onely of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtachius</hi> and <hi>Theopiſta</hi> (whom they knew were unhappy) they ask'd nothing, but ſaluted, and ſaluted them again. They joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully taking up their poor bundle, and holding each a Child by the hand, expected with gladneſs when the Bark (which was near the Land) would ſtrike ſail, and caſt anchor; which no ſooner was done, but the Paſſengers quickly clearing the Veſſel, went aſhore, <hi>Euſtachius</hi> excepted, whoſe departure certain Mariners of ſet purpoſe deferr'd.</p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:46454:49"/>
               <p>With eyes ſeeming big with indignation, and were onely ſwoln with love, Whither go'ſt thou, came out roaring the Maſter of the Ship, whither go'ſt thou, foul Thief? who ſhall pay me? How troubled poor <hi>Euſtachius</hi> remain'd at thoſe words, 'twould be too ſad a thing to conceive; who quickly foreſaw, that to his great prejudice, his departure with the reſt was ſuſpended. His threats, ſuperfluous to one diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arm'd, and miſerable, preſaged this furious mans guilt; the ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude they ſought after, bearing witneſs of their enterprize, that it needed no teſtimony.</p>
               <p>Poor <hi>Euſtachius</hi> reply'd, I go where I hope my neceſſities will be mercifully ſupply'd, Heaven will content thee, which is ſo juſt, it never ſuffer'd Charity to go unrewarded, or wickedneſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed.</p>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:46454:50"/>
               <p>Neither Charity, nor Heaven, ever rigg'd yet my Ships, ſaid the Maſter, or paid my Men their wages. Who's there? ſeize on his Wife.</p>
               <p>Then <hi>Euſtachius</hi> and <hi>Theopiſta</hi> fell down on their knees, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring with their tears, to pay him at leaſt with compaſſion, ſince they could not for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent pay him otherwiſe, ſought humbly to appeaſe him.</p>
               <p>What can this poor man pay, who hath nothing of his own, but the trouble of maintaining with his hands, himſelf, his Wife, and Children? If this poor Bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle will content you, he ſaid, I give it you moſt willingly: But what will you do with theſe few rags, which (to preſerve us from the injury of the weather) are left us of our fortune, not to eaſe, but deride us.</p>
               <p>Diſpatch, reply'd the barbarous
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:46454:50"/>Lover. Then going to <hi>Theopiſta,</hi> who being now Captive, was led as a Priſoner into the Cabbin; Weep not, he ſaid ſoftly to her, weep not my dear, I claim thee alone as my reward, but not for the ſervice of my Bark, but my heart. <hi>Euſtachius</hi> (whoſe Valour, which us'd to be victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, was not yet extinguiſh'd) reſolving to dye, or recover his Wife, leap'd with ſuch fury to the ground, that he ſhew'd what an influence grief often hath on gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry. But what could he do? Thoſe Sea-Tigers threatned with their Swords, their Bows, and Scy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitars, to kill before his face in an inſtant his Children; if he ſpake a word more, or ſtirr'd a foot further.</p>
               <p>At this ſo ſad encounter, <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtachius</hi> his heart left his boſome, and his courage his heart. But what will be the iſſue? Ah I cannot penetrate it, and much leſs deſcribe
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:46454:51"/>it. This vaſt diſaſter deprived him likewiſe of the little conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation which weeping affords. All grief is contumacious, but this hath ſo much power, it turns Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant. His breaſt claſp'd his heart in his breaſt, being afraid to ſee it murther'd by ſorrow. His legs could not bear him from the ground, for the power that gave them motion (call'd to help where there was greater need) could not do its office in a place ſo remote from the heart; ſo as the vital parts diſagreeing, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nac'd ruine to the fabrick of his body. The blood (leaving pale all the members) retir'd altogether in defence of that part the life doth flow from. His ſoul was all reduc'd into his eyes, for onely by that paſſage it could finde a way to the languiſhing heart. He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, and made an end many times, before he had begun to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:46454:51"/>Grief that may be vented, is too weak; neither naturally can we loſe without torment, what we love to poſſeſs. He ſtood long on the ſhore, amaz'd, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable, and ſenſeleſs. Each little diſtance would have made him thought one of the ſtones which Ships are faſtned to. He ſpake not at all, but when he now turned his eyes from the Bark to his Children, or from his Children to the Bark.</p>
               <p>Woe's me, he ſeem'd to ſay, with his eyes ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her querulous, than weeping<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> woe's me, that Veſſel is fraught with nothing, but onely our di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ters. O poor young Children, and innocently unfortunate, behold there your life and mine ſails away. Ah, I ſaid amiſs; God would have her go; Ah, ſhe is forced away. Weep little ones, weep ye, ſhe is forced away; ſhe began to ſuffer
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:46454:52"/>violence, even between our arms. What ſhall we Wretches do? Is that the Bark which carries her? O too cruel eyes, why ſhew ye it me? Hitherto I have wept for what I have loſt, but now I muſt begin to bewail what is left me. What ſhew ye me, O cruel eyes? Dear Wife, whither goeſt thou? who robs me of thee, the eaſe onely of my tribulations, and the onely tribulation I reſent? Whither goeſt thou, poor <hi>Theopi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta?</hi> whither goeſt thou <hi>Theopiſta,</hi> who to no other end ſurviv'dſt the tempeſt, but to finde a more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous haven than ſhipwrack it ſelf? For what art thou reſerv'd? I never thought the time would have come, that I ſhould have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd (and with pity) to have had thee ſlain by thunder, and ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack'd. We have loſt our Goods, our Slaves, our Herds, and our Countrey, yet none of theſe loſſes
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:46454:52"/>is ſo great, as that of not loſing our ſelves among the rocks. And O thou Sea, that only would'ſt be calm'd with my miſery, why didſt not drown that Bark, where the Husband in the boſome of his Wife, and the Wife with her arms about the neck of her Husband, (though they had loſt their lives) would not now have loſt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of each other. Ah, my cruel fate (to make me more unhappy than any ever was) would have me ſuffer ſhipwrack no where elſe, but on the ſhore.</p>
               <p>So he ſeem'd to ſpeak, with his eyes full of grief, looking ſometimes towards the Veſſel, which now was out of ſight, and ſometimes turning himſelf to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his Children, expoſed to want by misfortune, and not any fault of their Mother. But he ſpake not ſo couragiouſly before, reſembling <hi>Moſes</hi> at the foot
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:46454:53"/>of <hi>Sinai,</hi> the place of tribulation; who the more it did thunder on the mountain, remain'd the more undaunted, and got the more ground.</p>
               <p>Let's go hence children, he ſaid, let's go hence my ſons, God is not pleaſed we ſhall have any longer the company of dear <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſta;</hi> his ſacred will be done; he takes her away, that gave her to us; and I cannot e're believe, that he, who beſtow'd her ſo juſt, will let her be corrupted and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prav'd. Let's wholly and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly ſubmit to his good pleaſure, and then he'll be ſure to defend, preſerve, and comfort her. Ah heart! too pitifull a heart! why tak'ſt thou it ill? Deſir'ſt thou what God will not have? I am glad of it, that thou mayſt not grieve, becauſe the more ſenſible thou ſhalt be of this loſs, the more meritorious will be thy content,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:46454:53"/>and this thy oblation more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted. Would'ſt not loſe wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly thy ſelf for the love of thy God? and why not thy Wife? How know'ſt thou, God takes her not from thee, to preſerve her from the dangers peradventure thou might'ſt leade her into? Ah dear <hi>Theopiſta,</hi> where art thou? whither goeſt thou? who robs me of thee, O onely Port of all my diſaſters? who deprives me of thee, O onely conſolation of all my afflictions? whither leadſt me, wicked ſorrow? Yes, yes, 'tis but juſtice ſhe is taken from me. And how was I worthy of ſo good a Wife, ſo religious a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, that have been wicked, ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual, and ingratefull; and having ſo bountifull a God, have taken up my reſt, and confin'd (which is worſe) my affections, in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of a Woman, for my haven and comfort? Yes, yes, my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:46454:54"/>
                  <hi>Theopiſta,</hi> go as far as thou art dear unto me, and I love thee. May I ſeek no more delight any where, but in thee alone, O dear and loving God, O God, the hope of my hope; O God, the onely delight of my future delights. Farewell <hi>Theopiſta,</hi> poor <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſta,</hi> God will preſerve thee, whoſe holy will alwayes be done. Let's go hence, little Sons, let's go hence; ſhe's gone, be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent; God will be our <hi>Theopiſta,</hi> and comfort, accompany, and protect us.</p>
               <p>So when he had fitted his leaſt Son on the truſs at his back, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying the other in his boſome, and ſupporting himſelf, with the hand he had free, on a poor and mean ſtaff, he follow'd the way that ſeem'd the moſt beaten.</p>
               <p>O how many times, call'd back by affection, turned he towards the Bark<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which he could onely
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:46454:54"/>ſee in his minde. Farewell Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, farewell <hi>Theopiſta,</hi> this is the laſt farewell; I no longer call thee mine, for God is not pleas'd to have thee ſo longer. Thanks be to God for all things. Let's go hence little Sons, poor little Sons; God is not pleas'd <hi>Theopiſta</hi> ſhould be lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger with us; God will be our <hi>Theopiſta,</hi> and be his will done. As ſoon as we ſhall finde an Habitation, that is capable of our miſeries, I'le act the part of <hi>Theopiſta,</hi> I'le provide for you, get ready your meat, and bleſs it; I'le teach you Gods name, and how to thank and praiſe him; ye ſhall not want comfort, let's onely go hence. Farewell <hi>Theopiſta,</hi> God will be with thee. 'Tis time <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtachius,</hi> to begin to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the beſt way, in which God direct us, to finde out
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:46454:55"/>the place he would have us go to. This way is the directeſt, let's go here. Ah poor <hi>Theopiſta,</hi> God knows how thy heart beats, which is ſo remote from thy dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>Euſtachius.</hi> God knows what thou endureſt, and knows what thou feareſt. Be confident, be confident God will not forſake thee.</p>
               <p>Relying in this manner on God, and offering up often, and ſuppreſſing his ſorrow, he advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced ſo far, that coming in the night to certain poor houſes, he was treated there charitably till the morning. What reſt he took that night, let him conceive that knows. The Children cry'd con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually, calling on their Mother, but in vain, unleſs they call'd on her to wound the heart of their poor and diſconſolate Father. Imagine what affliction <hi>Euſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius</hi> was in, who with his own
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:46454:55"/>diſaſters, was forc'd to eaſe others. O God, what condition!</p>
               <p>When the day appeared, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming his ſad burthen, and thanking his Hoſt for his charity, informed himſelf of the way, and departed. To loſe no time, and free his minde from thoughts, and the thoughts of the difficulty of the way, he ſometimes recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended <hi>Theopiſta</hi> to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of Heaven, and ſometimes gave God thanks for the benefits he had receiv'd. He ſometimes renew'd the oblation and ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of his will, and ſometimes begg'd ſtrength againſt ſo many tribulations. He gave God thanks, that he thought him not compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of Plaiſter, and pray'd he might be worthy of victory. Sometimes his little Sons ask'd him queſtions, and ſometimes begg'd ſomething; and he now with words, now with bread,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:46454:56"/>gave eaſe to their ſufferings. His Childrens vivacity and ſpirit, was no ſmall conſolation to him, who call'd them the ſtaff of his old age, the Companions of his exile, and Aſſwagers of his cares; and for their education, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd them the ſervice of God, to make them ſhare more of his virtue, than fortune. He repos'd many times, &amp; then perhars ſlept, his wearineſs, his ſorrow, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer watching, inviting him to it.</p>
               <p>At laſt, after many hours tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, they came to a Torrent, which was ſtony, and made a huge noyſe; the ſpace between whoſe banks was ſo great, the eye could not meaſure its diſtance. Having laid down his burthen, (not finding any one in that ſolitude to direct him) he reſolv'd to ſound the Foard; and laying his Sons to reſt, who lying on the graſs, began to play together,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:46454:56"/>he guided by his ſtaff, deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into the ſtream, and found the water arriv'd not to his knee, all the danger conſiſting in the breadth, and not the depth. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing returned to his Sons, he reſolv'd to waft them over; but to ſecure himſelf, he thought it the beſt to ſeparate the weight, and carry them over at twice. Having carry'd over one, he came back for the other; but getting up the bank, he had ſcarce diſcern'd the ſhore, when viewing the land with his eyes, he diſcover'd, ah ſight! poor <hi>Euſtachius</hi> diſcover'd a Lion, who ſtealing away his little Son, fled apace with the Prey in his mouth, but more peradventure out of greedineſs than fear, and juſt then va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd out of his ſight. Ah what ſaw he? Ah what will he do? Let's paſs by, O Pen, his affections, too bitter to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:46454:57"/>and too hard to be imitated. There's need of a veil, leſt the colours ſhould expreſs an affliction ſo great.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euſtachius</hi> ran faſter than the torrent he paſs'd. Woe's me, ſaid he, let us make haſt, leſt the other be likewiſe in danger. If God will let us have but one Son, one Son is enough; thanks be to God for what he hath left us, and thanks be to him, that his will is perform'd in the loſs of the other. O how many men, for one onely ſon, would call themſelves happy? If ſons prove a comfort, one one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is enough; but if otherwiſe, one onely is too much. Ah moſt unfortunate child, to be buried in the belly of a beaſt? Ah I am unhappy to beget thee for Lions. I thought I ſhould onely have had cauſe of complaining againſt Fortune for making me miſerable, but I finde I muſt complain as
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:46454:57"/>much of Nature, for making me a Father.</p>
               <p>Speaking in this manner, he came to the other bank; and run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and out of breath, when he got to the top, he began to ſay thus to the top, he began to ſay thus to his ſon; We have loſt thy little brother, a Lion hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd him; when he found, that the Wolves, which likewiſe had depriv'd him of the other, came howling, to partake of the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate Prey.</p>
               <p>At this ſad ſpectacle, what kinde of man may we phanſy the childleſs, afflicted, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted <hi>Euſtachius?</hi> I ſhould have call'd him Father; but cannot be ſo cruel to remember, he hath no more ſons.</p>
               <p>Hear ye ages, and wonder! Hear ye the Miracles of that powerfull God, who hath been alwayes wonderfull in his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants. <hi>Euſtachius,</hi> at that lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:46454:58"/>fight, humbling and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrating himſelf on the ground, began, weeping much, to cry out; O free, O happy ſtate, deſerving to be onely acknowledg'd from the hand of a mercifull God; we have nothing elſe to loſe, all our Goods are now ſecure, and our little Sons (ah little Sons!) got ſafely to the ſhore. What matter is't, if by ſhipwrack, or ſailing, they get to the land, provided they get thither with ſafety. Gods favours ſhould be grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully commemorated, and not expos'd to cenſure. Lets ſing, my Soul, let's ſing the mercies of ſo gratious a God. O free, O happy ſtate! We are in ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate, and ſecure a condition, that we have nothing elſe to fear or hope for. Fortune can threaten us no longer, ſhe can no longer trouble us, God be bleſſed and thank'd. O dear,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:46454:58"/>moſt loving and mercifull God, and when could I ever have imagin'd, being fetter'd with ſo many ſnares of the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil, I ſhould be ſo happy, to be free and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>engag'd from them all, and one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly depend on my will? On my will, which is now, and ever ſhall be thee, O my dearly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, the love of my ſoul, my God? Thou ſhalt be my Mother, my Wiſe, my Father, and Children; in thee are to be calm'd my affections, my miſeries, and thoughts; thou art to be the object of my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, the prey of my will, and the glory of my memory. And ſince thou haſt brought me to this happineſs, ſhall I have ſo rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſo ſtubborn, and ſo ſenſeleſs a heart, to bewail it when it comes? Ah my God, my heart is of fleſh, be pleas'd to forgive it; and of ſtone,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:46454:59"/>be pleas'd to ſplit it; draw from it the water, may ſet forth thy glory. From thee, in thee, and for thee, I proteſt for the future, all my thoughts, my affections, and words, ſhall begin, advance, and terminate. I proteſt, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever hath not thee for its object and center, my Creatour, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, and my God, (the name I alwayes finde the moſt ſweet) I will not approve of. I will no longer will any thing, but what thou would'ſt have me to will; nor love any thing, but what thou would'ſt have me to love. What is not of God, or for God, <hi>Euſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius</hi> ſhall not love, or deſire.</p>
               <p>So raiſing couragiouſly him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, (Ah, good men have affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions without, but conſolation within) as if he had endur'd no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing yet, he went on, beſeeching God to begin now at laſt to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe and try him.</p>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:46454:59"/>
               <p>And when, ſaid he, ſhall we ever have a better occaſion? when ever finde a time ſo oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, to ſuffer for Gods ſake? Afflictions are no longer impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to divert us from the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God, to which we are wholly devoted. Where are the tribulations and miſeries that were threatned? What hitherto we have ſuffered, was ill onely out of opinion, and what have we ſuffered of our own? Goods, Honours, Dignities, Wife, and Children, were no otherwiſe ours, than as troubles. And muſt it be call'd and eſteem'd a tribulation, to be rid of troubles, ſubjection, and impediments? Ah my God, and what do I ſuffer, for thy ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings for me? And what ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction do I make thee, for the many offences I ſo long have committed? When thou waſt pleas'd to ſuffer for me, didſt not
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:46454:60"/>willingly loſe thy Goods, thy Mother, and thy Countrey? Waſt not willingly torn in pieces, and crucify'd, and which is more than all, moſt innocently? And ſhall I wicked man, in my tribulations and ſorrows for my ſins, have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to relate, but that I was preſent at the ſufferings of others? If thou ſayſt I am ſo weak, I ſhall be diſcontented, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe unfortunate, if thou, who canſt not erre, haſt ſo low an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of the love I bear thee. For my own part I confeſs, that me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks I have more courage, and dare perform more. Give me, ah g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve me an affliction deſerving the teſtimony of my love, and let what is paſt be my penance. Let what I muſt yet ſuffer, be conſecrated wholly to the love, I conſume my ſelf in, for thy ſake; for I cannot endure to be a vulgar Servant to God. The
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:46454:60"/>favours thou haſt done me, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it, and my ſoul cannot ſuffer it, which bluſhes to be one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly known a Chriſtian, by not worſhipping of Idols. Hitherto my Wife hath been a Sufferer, my Children, and Slaves, and 'tis now high time I ſuffer ſomething for thy ſake, for thee, O my dear, moſt loving, and mercifull God.</p>
               <p>With theſe, and the like en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainments, <hi>Euſtachius</hi> went ſo far, that at laſt he arriv'd at a Village call'd <hi>Badiſo,</hi> whoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiredneſs and poverty ſo pleas'd him, he reſolv'd to fix there, if he could. The few perſons li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in that place, made it partly ſeem no deſart, though otherwiſe it was unfrequented, where they ſow'd what was neceſſary, to keep them alive; and not ſell, unleſs they ſold, not becauſe they
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:46454:61"/>poſſeſs'd, but becauſe they liv'd there. The place was remote e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough from <hi>Rome,</hi> to conceal him from fame; and as far from noyſe, as neceſſary to ſeparate the minde from the pleaſures of the world. There poverty was no ſhame, for riches were not known; nor us'd they treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries there, for intereſt commanded not. The men there diſſembled not, for there they did not covet; and the women did not ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to ſale, for they lov'd not for luſt, but to preſerve nature. The air was calm, the ſoyl very fertile, and the Inhabitants ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere. <hi>Euſtachius</hi> thought this place was agreeable to the life he had deſign'd; and therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commending himſelf unto God, for the illumination of his will, he ſought how to live. But he ſoon was entertain'd, as a Partner in thoſe rural affairs, by a good
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:46454:61"/>and poor man, of ſome little power there; but whether a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourer, or Maſter, I know not, for I know not if the tyrannie of dominion was in force at that time, in a place ſo retir'd.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euſtachius,</hi> giving thanks unto God for this ultimate favour, ſo willingly and induſtriouſly fell to tilling of the ground, that the Owner of the Village, being eas'd of his labour, and glad of his new ſervant, aſcrib'd and imputed to Heavens gentle influence, the arrival of this Pilgrim, to whoſe care now he committed all his buſineſs, and his poor eſtate.</p>
               <p>The Earth return'd ſo happily <hi>Euſtachius</hi> his labours, that the Maſter was aſtoniſh'd, who thought it impoſſible ſo ſmall a ſpot of ground ſhould abound in that manner. All that beheld it, thought it painted, and not till'd, it pleaſing as well the eye, as
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:46454:62"/>'twas uſefull for man's life. Each Turf brought forth Flowers, eve-Flower Fruit, and all Fruit grew ripe. The Seeds ſeem'd ranged into order, not ſcatter'd; and the Trees being lopp'd, ſhew'd the Husbandman's induſtry, by their growing the better. The Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows were pleaſant, the fallow ground manur'd, and every thing anſwer'd art, the eye, and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation, with increaſe, delight; and Plenty. Ah, O God, the ſighs of the Tiller were the South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt-winds, and his tears the dew, which made the ſoyl as fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile, as the Paradiſe of his ſoul.</p>
               <p>Fifteen years together liv'd <hi>Euſtachius,</hi> in this hard, but happy poverty; in which time he trafficking for eternity, and leading a life that was rather a meditation than life, diſcover'd to the world, how men may live on Earth, and yet dwell in
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:46454:62"/>Heaven. Every thing inform'd him of his Maker, and in every thing he found ſomething to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite him to a Virtue. If a little thin Cloud paſſed by, he reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renc'd it as a ſhadow of Gods preſence, and contemplated in the Heavens on his Palace, and in the Sun on his Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle. In each breath of air, he adored the Spirit of God, paſſing and triumphing on the wings of the winde. He either plow'd, mowed, or ſow'd, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver wanting occaſion of recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting himſelf. He grieved, that Man from the Earth, an inſenſible thing, could pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe himſelf a gratitude for each, though little, labour of his tilling; when he, who had a ſoul, and was rational, and more oblig'd to God than any other Creature, was cold, ſlow, and backward in retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:46454:63"/>him thanks, who cover'd him with the Heavens, warm'd him with the Sun, ſuſtain'd him on a Pavement of Flowers, and nouriſh'd him with plenty of all things drawn out of the ground. Every Flower put him in minde of a virtue. The whiteneſs of the Lilly made him bluſh to think, a Soul redeem'd by Chriſt, ſhould let a ſtinking Flower ſurpaſs it in purity. In every Roſe he found a thorn, piercing his heart, and upbraiding the little charity he expreſs'd for the love of his God, who crown'd and rent with thorns, was torn to ſave him. The herb Turnſole is never weary in following the tracks of the Sun, <hi>Euſtachius</hi> ſaid, mortifying himſelf; and wilt thou, O my heart, let a Flower inſtruct thee, in loving, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erving, and contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plating on thy God? The Hya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinth, in the opening of his leaves,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:46454:63"/>ſends forth ſweet and ſad notes; and he that bewails not his ſins in his heart, bewails them in the leaves. But what doth <hi>Euſtachi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> perform, who hath been ſo long, and continually a Sinner? Every green Herb taught him hope, and every fruitfull Tree imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. Theſe Meditations ended in extaſies of his minde, which ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd from the body, did run to the feet of his Creatour, to thank him for the fruit he had gather'd, as a benefit receiv'd; and the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mature fruit, as a benefit expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. Such was the life of <hi>Euſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius,</hi> in that ſolitude inhabited by Angels, who continually de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending and aſcending, as it were on <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Ladder, beheld and admired the love, which to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his Creatour he expreſſed, whom I cannot call earthly, ſince he alwayes liv'd in Heaven.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="book">
               <pb facs="tcp:46454:64"/>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:46454:64"/>
               <head>The Loving Husband, and Prudent Wife, &amp;c.</head>
               <head>The third Book.</head>
               <p>WHoſoever is thankfull to God in proſperity, pays his debts; but he that gives him thanks in adverſity, turns Creditor. Tribulation, ſayes Saint <hi>Jerome,</hi> is a fruit of the Almond-tree, the rinde of which is bitter, but the kernel very ſweet. And the Naturaliſts ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, when the Almond-tree is full of bloſſoms, 'tis a ſign of a
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:46454:65"/>plentifull harveſt. Our <hi>Euſtachi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> makes it good, whoſe ſufferings all know, which have been ſo great, their billows have petrify'd his heart, and render'd it ſtony, obdurate, and dead; to paſſions and affections. Under the bitter Plant of affliction, as <hi>Jacob</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Turpentine-tree, <hi>Euſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius</hi> hath bury'd the Idols of his affections, his intereſt, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires. His heart is no longer of fleſh, but of Chriſt; and had it been open'd, the name of <hi>Jeſus</hi> would have been found there, as in that of <hi>Ignatius</hi> the Martyr. But God would not permit him to continue in this ſtate. Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations may ſerve to increaſe his temptations, but cannot increaſe the faith of his invincible heart, which can have no addition of courage. The eagerneſs and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour he hath ſhew'd on all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, give him worthily the prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:46454:65"/>and title of a Noble Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander, who had been ſtill victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious. Here miſery made a ſtand, and Heaven clear'd up to this for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate Paſſenger.</p>
               <p>As <hi>Euſtachius</hi> was diſcourſing one day with certain Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, in order to their rural af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, two Strangers ſaluting them kindly, approached to them, whoſe civility the Country People returning, offer'd themſelves rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily to ſerve them in what they were able. The Strangers thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, ſeem'd moſt deſirous to have information of a Roman, call'd <hi>Placidus,</hi> who together with his Wife, and two Sons, had been miſſing fifteen years, and they were in queſt of.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euſtachius,</hi> who before had been their General, and their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate Friend, knew them, but was not known again. And who would e're have thought ſo pale,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:46454:66"/>ſo hairy, and ſo humble a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, colour'd onely with miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune, could have been the face of <hi>Placidus,</hi> who formerly full of majeſtie, and glittering like the Sun, repreſented in the Colours of his Banners, the Purple of his Triumphs.</p>
               <p>At this their encounter, and demands, <hi>Euſtachius</hi> could not chooſe but be ſenſible of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural commotions our frailty oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions; ſo as 'tis no wonder if the memory of himſelf, his Wife, and his Sons, cauſed him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent.</p>
               <p>The temptation was ſtrong, becauſe too unexpected, and had a too delicate opportunity, and too little ſuſpected. His Friends were the cauſe, whoſe affections, incommodity, and charity, (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs by not concealing them) he could not return. Quickly, but quietly, leſt he ſhould have been
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:46454:66"/>obſerv'd, he ſadly turn'd his back, and leaving the company, went weeping towards his home. His tears trickl'd down in too great an abundance, and he perceiv'd he wept, with a kind of afflicted ſenſuality (even tears, ſaid <hi>Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorus,</hi> have their luſt) which he ſoon was ſorry for.</p>
               <p>Woe is me, what do I? Men weep not in this manner for the eaſing of nature, whoſe ſorrows to appeaſe, many tears are not requiſite. Men weep in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, for ſome unruly paſſion, ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannically ſubduing their reaſon. Lets look to our ſelves, O <hi>Euſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius,</hi> leaſt the Devill circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent us, for this violence is too great.</p>
               <p>So he ſpake to himſelf, when invaded by the memory of his former proſperity, his love to his wife, and his grief for the death of his ſons, but conquer'd by his
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:46454:67"/>fear, to be ſeen by his God, too devoted to the world; he beſought his ſacred Majeſty, not to ſuffer any earthly affection to prevayle in his heart, which dedicated and bequeathed to him, was no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of <hi>Euſtachius,</hi> than as <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtachius</hi> could not ſerve without a heart, and love his gracious God.</p>
               <p>So with unknown reſentments, reſembling a trance, which might be thought a puniſhment for his ſorrow, but probably was the ſweetneſs, and fruit of his devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he fell to the earth, beſeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God to moderate ſo immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate a paſſion. He would have begg'd of God, as he was pleas'd to comfort him with the unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected preſence of two ſuch dear friends, ſo he would too be pleas'd (even once before he dy'd) to ſhew him his beloved <hi>Theopiſta,</hi> ſince he could not hope poſſibly,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:46454:67"/>to ſee his little ſons (ah little ſons) ſo unfortunately loſt, and bewayl'd.</p>
               <p>He would have purſu'd his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire with devout ſupplications, and prayers, if he could have been aſſur'd it was no temptation, he being ſo confirm'd, and onely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſe in the will of his Creator, that it ſeem'd to him a ſin to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire it. He ſo paſſionately was ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour'd of God, that he thought, if he lov'd any thing beſides him, 'twould decreaſe his love to God.</p>
               <p>Theſe his irreſolutions &amp; doubts expreſt his devotion and affection to God. Tis one of the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of a ſoul in the ſtate of grace, to ſee that all his thoughts, affections, and operations are prayers, incenſes, and merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious.</p>
               <p>To theſe ſupplications of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtachius,</hi> a voyce anſwer'd plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:46454:68"/>from Heaven, which ſpake in this manner. Be of good cheer, dear <hi>Euſtachius,</hi> I do not forget thee; O God, what expreſſions! O heart too hard, and too deafe! Doſt thou hear what God doth to his ſervants, and yet takeſt pleaſure in rebelling againſt him? Ah, what unhappineſs?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euſtachius</hi> encourag'd with this voyce, whoſe affectionate expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions may be eaſier imagin'd, than deſcrib'd, when he had ador'd, prais'd, and thank'd Almighty God, whoſe favours we return, when we gratefully acknowledge them, riſing from the ground, proceeded on his way. Every pace was a ſigh, and every ſigh an arrow, which he ſhot towards Heaven; Arrows not rebelling, but ejaculatory, ſhot-towards a ſweet enemy from an amorous heart, and not to offend, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke.</p>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:46454:68"/>
               <p>The ſhowrs, which fall with thunder, by <hi>Plutarch</hi> call'd fulgo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, are the beſt to water, and make the earth fruitfull, from whence they are exhal'd.</p>
               <p>He no ſooner was returned to his work, but his foreſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions came ſuddenly upon him, who being ſtill in motion, here only<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> excepted, ended fortunately their pilgrimage in this field, where their own conſolation, and Count<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yes felicity they found green and fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhing in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>Euſtachius.</hi> They relating the marks, and Characters of <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> and <hi>Theopiſta,</hi> enquired of him, if he could peradventure, g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve tydings of them, whom they asked ſo kindly after: he could not but be mov'd at their cordiall affection, and pity their ſufferings, in ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eking after him.</p>
               <p>Gentlemen, he reply'd, why ſeek yee him ſo earneſtly, and
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:46454:69"/>with ſuch inconveniency to your ſelves?</p>
               <p>Great things, ſaid the ſtrangers, of which our great love is the leaſt, induce us to ſeek him. He no more conquer'd by the love of his friends than the curioſity of ſenſe, conceal'd ſtill himſelf; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was charitable, &amp; deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to oblige them to his power, he ſayed he could not ſatisfy their demand, reply'd in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
               <p>'Tis now very late, and becauſe in this poor Country you will not find eaſily lodging, Ile wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly accomodate you this night, if you pleaſe to accept it. They receiv'd his moſt courteous invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, God ſo directing them, who diſpoſes of our hearts, and ſubordinates the means to the end. When they came into the houſe, and his maſter was withdrawn, he beſought him, in relation to his
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:46454:69"/>many years ſervice, to lodge the noble ſtrangers for a night. What can we deny to ſo uſefull, and ſo faithfull a ſervant? All ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyes in expreſſions of kindneſs, being ended, they ſate down to ſupper, where <hi>Euſtachius</hi> was the Cook, Sewer, Carver, and Cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearer, and made them all the Sauces, we can taſte, where cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity makes the feaſt.</p>
               <p>In the mean time, while the ſtrangers diſcourſed of <hi>Euſtachi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> his kindneſs, and entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they thought they ſaw ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing extraordinary in his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and behaviour, which they were acquainted with. The more they heard him ſpeak, and partak'd of his Charity, the more clearly they thought his face con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd them he was <hi>Placidus,</hi> the end of their travaile, and object of their thoughts, whoſe health they drank, and onely ſpake of.</p>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:46454:70"/>
               <p>God knows, where we may finde him, they ſaid, how he lives, and who ſhall be ſo happy to diſcover him. His ſons are now men, and his wife, if ſhe be li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> muſt be old. God knows, if we ſhall know them, if we meet them, and if they'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> know us.</p>
               <p>Theſe ſad, and affectionate remembrances made <hi>Euſtachius</hi> now and then ſhed a teare, and though he did all in his Power to ſuppreſs them, the violence he uſed gave his friends an opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to perceive him much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd, by his labouring ſo vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently to conceal them.</p>
               <p>The ſtrangers wonder, and ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition perſwaded them to doubt (if we doubt what we deſire) he was <hi>Placidus,</hi> ſo as among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves they began in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
               <p>Dear <hi>Antiochus,</hi> I take him for <hi>Placidus,</hi> when the other,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:46454:70"/>call'd <hi>Acatius,</hi> reply'd, I doubt it very much. His age and ſtature agree well with <hi>Placidus,</hi> his voice is the ſame, and his ſhape not unlike: But where are his wife, and his ſons? why ſhould he conceale himſelf from us? from us, who have been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways his ſervants, and lovers of his family, and name? But if he be not <hi>Placidus,</hi> what meane his compaſſionate looks, and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted ſobs, the greateſt ſignes of love? Ah tis he, the firſt reply'd quickly, but ſoftly ſaid the ſecond, grant he be the ſame (but we are not ſo happy) he cannot be hid from us; <hi>Placidus</hi> in the nape of his neck, hath the skar of a wound, which, if it be he, will aſſure us of the truth. Indeed ſaid <hi>Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus,</hi> you ſay very well, and therefore let's look there imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately. Ah, if we ſhall not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover it, the pleaſure, we receive
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:46454:71"/>by this hope, will too ſoon have an end. So between hope &amp; fear, they went to <hi>Euſtachius,</hi> and loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king on that part of his neck, which ends in his right ſhoulder, they found and read the chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter of the changes of fortune, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented in his life. I know not if they wept, nor can expreſs their ſorrow, for tears had no roome in two hearts ſo full of joy, ſo as it was neceſſary to deferre it: Their tears fell in ſhowres, not in drops, two eyes being too few for ſo ſweet an affliction.</p>
               <p>Ah long'd for <hi>Placidus,</hi> and why didſt conceale thy ſelf from us? from us, whom ſo often thou haſt call'd the faithfull friends of all thy fortune? By what fault of ours haſt thou been induc'd to live in a condition, in which to hide thy ſelf, its uſefull to thee, or may procure thy ſhame to be known unto us?</p>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:46454:71"/>
               <p>Can there be ſo ill a ſtate (when tis for thy advantage to own it) can make us affrayd? Hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune Peradventure, among its Many evills, a diſeaſe that kills gratitude and love? Ah <hi>Placidus,</hi> and what have we done to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit this rigour? If thou art deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to conceale thy ſelf from fame, to be known unto us, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veales thee not to any. We have found thee, if thou wilt, and if thou wilt not, our diſcovery of thee ſhall but ſerve to this end, that even in this place, we have ſought thee. Thou canſt not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to be known unto us, unleſs thou wilt deny us the reward our paines juſtly claime for ſeeking thee ſo long. This, thy vertue will not ſuffer us to fear, and our hearts cannot credit, which have always lov'd thee ſo, that we cannot leave ſeeking thee, not when thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'ſt not, to be found, not when
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:46454:72"/>thou thy ſelf think'ſt thy ſelf in ſuch a ſtate, deſerves to be even avoyded by thy ſelf.</p>
               <p>Theſe tears were let fall by his courteous co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panions; to whom <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtachius</hi> was willing to be known, when he ſaw he was diſcover'd.</p>
               <p>Friends, he reply'd, the very ſame affection that cauſes your ſorrow for my ſolitude, is the thing that occaſions, and deſerves it. The more dearly ye love me, the more juſtly ye deſerve I ſhould conceale from you the irkſome. information of my ſtate. When I could no longer ſerve you in any thing, but by hindering my cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, to diſturb your repoſe, I retyr'd in this habit, much leſſe grievous than my fortune. I thought I was unhappy enough, without taking one me the ſorrow of others. For this onely reaſon I declined your preſence, and now beg your Pardon, for being diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient.
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:46454:72"/>I was in ſo low an ebb of fortune, that having nothing left me to loſe, but my friends, I thought my love to them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blig'd me to leave them, to prevent their being taken from me.</p>
               <p>K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſes interrupted theſe excuſes, by drowning and ſtifling them in tears and embraces. They were forc't to be ſilent, becauſe they were forced to weep, and could not find words to expreſs ſo great a love. But their joyes quickly ended, for no ſooner <hi>Antiochus,</hi> had obtained a truce of his paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but turning to <hi>Euſtachius,</hi> he ask'd him for <hi>Trajana,</hi> and his two young, and beautifull ſons, who, inferiour in nothing but number, to the Graces, were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mir'd by the people of <hi>Rome,</hi> who wiſht the Latin Empire might perpetually abound with perſons of like valour.</p>
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:46454:73"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euſtachius</hi> recounted all the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents, which befell <hi>Theopiſta,</hi> and his ſons, at whoſe moſt unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate, and dreadfull remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, if his two dear compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions did not kill themſelves with weeping, 'twas by reaſon of their horrour and amazement at the tragicall relation.</p>
               <p>Many of the inhabitants of the village, where the fame was ſoon ſpread of <hi>Euſtachius</hi> his quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, brake off their diſcourſes and complements, by their concourſe to them, who with gladneſs, and confuſion mix'd together, came to ſee, and do him homage, and there was none amongſt them ſo rude that relented not, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in what manner, and how roughly, the braveſt ſouldier li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving had been depreſs'd by for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune.</p>
               <p>All of them amaz'd at ſuch ſtrange revolutions, began to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayle
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:46454:73"/>his departure, as foreſeen, and eſpecially they who juſt came to ſee him, as the two dear Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions related, how <hi>Trajan</hi> (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving to chaſtize a certain na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for pillaging temerariouſly, and depopulating the Confines of the Empire) expected only <hi>Placi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus,</hi> whoſe valour alone was ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to paralell the greatneſs of ſo dangerous an enterprize. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catius</hi> and <hi>Antiochus</hi> affirm'd, that <hi>Trajan</hi> had often been ſorry for the diſtance and misfortune of <hi>Placidus,</hi> and particularly in this occaſion, ſo as propoſing many rewards, and preferments to the bringer of him back, he had ſent into all Countrey, to enquire ſtrictly after him,</p>
               <p>The good, and honeſt Peaſants were afflicted, when they knew he muſt depart, who cauſed <hi>Badi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo</hi> to be envy'd by the Capitol. They thought when <hi>Euſtachius</hi>
                  <pb n="136" facs="tcp:46454:74"/>departed, ſerenity would depart from their clime, and fertility from the ſoyl. Ah, ſaid they, when he is gone from us, who ſtill was ſo ready to help every one, ſo kind, and ſo uſefull, whither ſhall we go for Counſell, aſſiſtance, and a pattern?</p>
               <p>The better part of night was conſum'd in ſo many, and ſuch different narrations, and conflicts of love, ſo as they were forc'd to repoſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euſtachius</hi> alone indefatigably ſpent the reſidue of the night in commending himſelf to his God, and beſeeching him, to guide and protect him to the place, where he might ſpend his life, and Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice his death in his ſervice. He rememberd, he had heard from Gods own mouth, he ſhould be reſtor'd to his former condition, ſo as knowing 'twas Gods Will (to comport himſelf always, in every
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:46454:74"/>thing to the will of his Creator) he reſolv'd to go thence with his friends, to ſee in what God would employ and command him: when the dawning of the day began to appear in that Heaven, which ſurpaſs'd each thing in clearneſs, but the heart of our gallant Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier, they all roſe.</p>
               <p>The art the world uſes in laughing, and weeping, in order to intereſt, and not to affection, is the cauſe, that to deſcribe with how many tears, the departure of <hi>Euſtachius</hi> was accompany'd, will not ſhew with what ſorrow, he was ſeen to depart, of all the Countrey-people, who flocking to him, embrac'd, attended him, &amp; wept, and he that firſt return'd, ended firſt the neceſſity of leaving him.</p>
               <p>By his friends, who were co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piouſly provided of all things, he was clad in the journey, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:46454:75"/>to his quality, where the trouble they had, was not long, for they guided by the ſoft, and gentle gale of Gods grace, arriv'd in thirty dayes at the haven ſo deſired.</p>
               <p>The fame of his coming out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtript him, ſo as at his arrivall in <hi>Rome,</hi> he found the City full of acclamations for him, where the joy, and honours he was receiv'd with, unleſs we'll do them wrong, are incapable of relation. He en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd the City in triumph, if ever any triumph was accompany'd with applauſes of that kinde, where every ſtreet was a Capitoll, and every voyce a Panegerique. Nor was it at all neceſſary to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort him againſt pride, for he went as compos'd, and modeſt, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a child of Heaven. This was a triumph o're fortune, which conquerd, and ſuppreſs'd by his vertue, beheld him paſs to glory
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:46454:75"/>on a Chariot of hearts, and wills. When they came to the Palace, embraces tyr'd the day, where the the Emperour met him, embraced, and honour'd him, and inform'd of his adverſities, could not think of them, but with ſorrow. Each ear diſtill'd into Pitty, that liſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to his diſaſters, whoſe fortune would have had the name of tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedy, if it had not had a gallant Cavalier for the ſubject.</p>
               <p>When the Emperour, and the Orders of the City had receiv'd him with ſo many, and ſo glorious expreſſions of kindneſs, the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and reaſons of the war, were imparted to <hi>Euſtachius</hi> by <hi>Trajan,</hi> in whoſe Cabinet he learnt, that the happineſs of Princes reſides altogether in the chamber of Preſence, beyond which, the ſecreteſt rooms have onely the greatneſs of troubles, and cares. He found that <hi>Trajan,</hi>
                  <pb n="140" facs="tcp:46454:76"/>diſmayd with the greatneſs of the conſpiracy, the diſtance of the place, difficulty of proviſions, and inſufficiency, and infidelity of his miniſters of State, prepar'd for a war, which reaſon repreſented as dangerous, as neceſſary, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evitable, for the honour of his Crown.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euſtachius</hi> particularly inform'd of <hi>Trajans</hi> deſignes, ſo c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on them, that the Emperour perceiv'd, Victory is the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Counſell, and where prudence ſpeaks, fortune, tis probable, will ceaſe to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant, and find fixed ſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Trajan,</hi> without making more ado, relying altogether on the Vertue and Courage of <hi>Euſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius</hi> made him publiquely the Generall, and recommending to him the glory of the Latin Empire, remanded him ſo fraught with his
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:46454:76"/>favours, that had it not been ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice to advance by all poſſible means the honour of his Maſter, gratitude would have put him in minde of returning the benefits of ſo gracious and generous a Prince.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Euſtachius</hi> had muſter'd the Army, ſettled each Command, and provided all ſorts of ammuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he marched towards the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, but the name of the enemy, and how the war was manag'd, antiquity hath not left it ſo clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to us, as (without doing wrong to the truth of the ſtory) to deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> particulars. This may be enough, that <hi>Euſtachius</hi> conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the difficulties of a tedious &amp; dangerous way, and often con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting with the incommodities of hunger, the outrages of ill wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ambuſhes of the adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, diſcover'd, cop'd, fought with him, and o'rcame him.</p>
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:46454:77"/>
               <p>When he had ſubdu'd the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell, he ſecured the Empire to the Emperour, and remuſtering his ſouldiers, renown'd by the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and enricht with the booty, reſolv'd to retreat. But 'twould not be amiſſe, to relate the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionate charity, with which he commiſerating the unfortunate, moderated the anger of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querours, reſtrain'd the rapacity of the Covetous, and repreſſed the fierceneſs of the luſtfull, telling them with arguments, but more efficaciouſly by his own example, that victories are diſhonour'd by acts of injuſtice, and we make an ill return of Heavens favours, when we do commit cruelties. It would peradventure be conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, and perhaps not unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, to tell the love, and tears, he devoutly expreſt, for the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of graces from God, but who can deſcribe the conceptions
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:46454:77"/>of an Angel? Graces he receiv'd, and was thankfull for them; and was thankfull, becauſe he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd them; and receiv'd them, becauſe he was thankfull. He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd them ſo affectionatly, that oftentimes the graces loſing the name of graces, became the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of his gratitude; his zeal making him ſo deſerving, that the favours he receiv'd, made him capable of deſerving them afreſh. O moſt happy ſtate of a Soul in love with God!</p>
               <p>The Army marched, and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in order, every pace being regular, in reſpect of their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and conveniency of the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. The Van-guard, Battalia, and Reer-guard, with the Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage, and Proviſions, in their place. Light-Horſmen ſcowr'd the way, though the Countrey was open, and no danger of am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſhes, and the Precurſors went
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:46454:78"/>for Forrage, as the way was commodious. In every thing they provided againſt the perils of a War, and enjoy'd in every thing the delights of a Peace. They marched in order, not out of ſuſpicion, but diſcipline, for their Arms ſerv'd onely for the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, and not the defence of the Souldier. At the end of ſome dayes, <hi>Euſtachius</hi> arriving in a pleaſant and fruitfull part of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> reſolved the Army ſhould repoſe for ſome time, which, by reaſon of its hard and toylſome march, was in no good condition. During the ſweetneſs of this reſt, the Souldiers allur'd by the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantneſs of the Countrey, went recreating themſelves in that Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe of <hi>Egypt,</hi> whoſe boſome ſtill enamell'd with a Spring of ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Treaſures, invited them with pleaſure and tranquillity to lye every where on the ground.</p>
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:46454:78"/>
               <p>It happened on a time, that two of them declining the heats at noon day, were reſting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in a ſhade of Palm-trees, where a Garden lay conceal'd, which for the delights of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants, was ſeated in the moſt remote part of the Houſe.</p>
               <p>They lay ſolitary on the graſs, and talking among themſelves; and becauſe the conveniency of the place, and the time unfit for buſineſs, gave them the opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, they paſſing from one to another diſcourſe, informed each other by turns of the ſtate and condition of their fortunes.</p>
               <p>A poor Woman, that was ſpin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning behind the hedge of the neighbouring Garden, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing her ſelf in the ſhade, heard all their diſcourſe, and things; which not onely caus'd amazement in her heart, but drew tears from her eyes. She toſs'd up
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:46454:79"/>and down diſorder'd, and much troubled; reſolves to change the climate, to make uſe of the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings ſhe received by chance. But how will ſhe be able to do it, ſince ſhe is ſo unhappy, that to call her a Woman of ſmall fortune, would detract from her cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity?</p>
               <p>While theſe mental tumults la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, her minde gave her, happily the General, if ſhe made it her ſuit, would eaſily condiſcend to her modeſt deſires.</p>
               <p>She, who had her heart and her ears repleniſh'd with the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated piety of <hi>Euſtachius,</hi> em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brac'd the ſuggeſtion; and arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving at the place, where ſhe heard he was quarter'd, continues her requeſt for acceſs, and eaſily ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd it of him; who never a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham'd to have his actions ſeen, retires to live more quietly, and not to ſin more ſecretly. She found
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:46454:79"/>him ſitting in the midſt of his Champions, the glory of that age, where I might ſay, he recreated himſelf, if treating of a Hero, it came not near impiety, not to ſay, he was at Councel. She firſt proſtrating her eyes, and then kneeling, rather owning the title of a noble and modeſt Maid, than a mature and beggarly Egyptian, ſpake to him in this manner.</p>
               <p>You ſee, my Lord, a poor un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Creature, who hath loſt all that Heaven and Nature could give her. Time and Fortune have robb'd me of my Youth, my Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, Countrey, Means, Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and Sonnes. But Heaven be praiſed, whoſe decrees ſhould be alwayes held in reverence, nothing elſe is left me; but the dreggy part of my age, which being vile, infirm, frail, impotent, and painfull, begins now ſo to trouble me, I am oblig'd to think
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:46454:80"/>of my Grave, to prevent my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing miſerable, even after death. <hi>Rome</hi> was my Countrey, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther naturall affection calls me, the onely favour I have left me to beg for ſo wretched a Carcaſs. I beſeech you, Noble Sir, deny not my requeſt, that I may at your charitable charge once again ſee that ſoyl, which though it gave me ſo unfortunate a birth, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves my love ſo well, I never ſhall remember it, but with tears, and with ſighs.</p>
               <p>Theſe few, and ſweet words, which ſhe utter'd with humility, and a modeſty expreſſing maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, the ſtanders by mov'd with compaſſion, commended extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euſtachius,</hi> who never was more happy and contented, than when he had occaſion to exerciſe his piety, approaching to her, who continu'd yet kneeling, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd;
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:46454:80"/>Poor Woman, thou ſhalt receive comfort. Thy diſcretion bears thee witneſs, thy birth is as thou ſay'ſt. Reſt ſatisfied, I will take ſuch order, thou ſhalt be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided of all things in the journey, and go along with us to the place thou deſireſt.</p>
               <p>On the ſudden the good Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, when ſhe heard him ſay ſo, as if ſhe had been ſtruck to the heart, lifting up her eyes, and fixing them on the countenance of the General, being diſmay'd, amaz'd, and pale, with a certain diſtemper, which ſome did inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret confuſion, and others aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, ſtood ſtill without mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Every one admiring the ſtrangeneſs of the thing, fell a gueſſing at the cauſe produced ſo ſudden a paſſion. But the pale and wan colour in her cheeks, became quickly a fine red; and as ſoon as her minde had obtain'd
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:46454:81"/>ſome peace to ſo many perturba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſhe endeavour'd with her tears to vent her great paſſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euſtachius</hi> more amaz'd than the reſt, and urging her to tell the ſudden cauſe of ſo ſenſible a ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, offer'd to aſſiſt her more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly, if ſhe needed, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd it.</p>
               <p>The iſſue was thus; when the Woman had calmed her paſſion, and was confident of the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals magnanimity, ſhe beſought him at laſt, that diſmiſſing the Company, he would ſuffer her, for a ſhort ſpace of time, to ſpeak to him alone, about buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs concerning her. <hi>Euſtachius</hi> condeſcended, and all the ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders by went away, leaving her ſhut in, and alone with the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral; who longing, irreſolute, and wavering, by reaſon of many doubts, gueſs'd, penetrating with his judgment, what the Beggar
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:46454:81"/>would ſay, who was not, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a great myſterie, ſo grievouſly, and ſuddenly afflicted.</p>
               <p>They diſcourſed long together, ſo as they who were without, were a great while onely curious; but when the length of time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to exceed what they thought in probability was enough to diſpatch ſuch mean affairs, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazement ſucceeded.</p>
               <p>And what things deſerving ſo tedious a Seſſion, do the tears of a deſpicable Woman deſign? What counſels does ſo valiant and ſo honoured a Champion im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, or receive from a Female of no worth? While they mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur'd in this manner, a Sergeant, whom the General called, at laſt enter'd in, who quickly returning with a pale and troubled coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, obſequiouſly and haſtily ſhut the door of the Chamber. How amaz'd they were at that,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:46454:82"/>I cannot relate, their wonder even making them dye of fear. Ah, what's the matter? All came about the nimble Meſſenger, asking him earneſtly the cauſe of his paleneſs and ſollicitude.</p>
               <p>Sirs, he reply'd, great things are ſure amiſs, but what, I could not penetrate: but I found the General weeping, who ſo often with dry eyes hath ſeen the doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full dangers of Victory, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned and o'recome the horrours of death. I am ſeeking certain Souldiers he commanded ſhould be brought to him preſently, and hinder not his ſervice.</p>
               <p>The Souldiers he ſought after, were the very ſame Men whoſe diſcourſe the ſame day the poor Woman had heard and obſerv'd behind the hedge of the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den.</p>
               <p>'Twas not long e're he came back, accompanied by the two
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:46454:82"/>Souldiers; who hearing with what trouble and impatience the General expected them, were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, and half dead. The pale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in their faces was interpreted by the Waiters, as the mark of an ill conſcience; and every one look'd ſtrangely upon them, as well becauſe they thought they were guilty of the Generals ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, whom they lov'd, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, if they were deſtin'd to ill fortune, 'twas neceſſary to begin to declare, they had no amity with them. Friendſhip dyes, when Calamity is born. Even this increas'd the horrour of the Wretches, who the more they were us'd to be reſpected, as being Lanciers, and ſitting at the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral's Table, bewail'd with grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter terrour, the contempt and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſteem ſhew'd to them in this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion. <hi>Euſtachius</hi> inform'd of their arrival, gave order to the
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:46454:83"/>Sergeant, to uſher them in, who commanded immediately to go out, return'd to his Companions to raiſe new doubts among them; who perplex'd, panted after the knowledge of ſuch ſtrange and impenetrable nows. <hi>Euſtachius</hi> not long after, cry'd aloud, ſo as every one, attentive to hear what ſucceeded, heard reſound from the Chamber, though ſhut, a lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table confuſion of weeping, and ſobs.</p>
               <p>They irreſolute awhile, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded at laſt, they were bound to go in, to ſee if they were able to do their Lord ſervice. But the Chamber being open'd, they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maz'd, and more diſorder'd than before, found, (ah wonder!) found, that their valiant Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander, proſtrate between two Souldiers, and a deſpicable Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, lay pitifully weeping, like a drooping little Boy, that had
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:46454:83"/>been correctedd for his faults.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euſtachius</hi> no ſooner beheld them, but riſing from the ground, and inſtantly looking chearfull, cry'd aloud unto them, Come in Brethren, come in; I invite you to behold the unſpeakable won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Gods providence and mercies. The joy his words oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion'd, which were far more pleaſing than they could imagine, ſurpaſs'd each affection in the breaſts of the Auditors, curioſity excepted. When they were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd in, he re-ſpake in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
               <p>Behold here, O Friends, my Wife, and my Sons, the chances of whoſe loſſes will eternally be famous in the Diaries of my Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes.</p>
               <p>He recounted here particularly to them, how his Wife had long ſince been violently taken from him by an amorous Robber; and
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:46454:84"/>how by the favour of Heaven, ſhe preſerv'd undefil'd, ſurviving the barbarous Fellow, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly neceſſitous, came begging to the ſervice of a Garden, behind whoſe hedge ſhe had the occaſion of re-knowing her Sons, who contracting a friendſhip, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating the unfortunate accidents of each others fate, were known to be Brothers.</p>
               <p>All ran on the ſudden by turns, to embrace and do homage unto their new Lords; by whom they were inform'd of the manner, how the one by Shepherds re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd out of the mouth of a Wolf, and the other by Peaſants out of the paws of a Lion, had, ſpending their time in a mean e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation, been at laſt by a Drum recall'd to their natural inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Acclamations ſoon began, the uſual Companions of felicity;
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:46454:84"/>each one affirming, he admir'd how 'twas poſſible they took not before for <hi>Placidus</hi> his Sons, thoſe valiant young Gentlemen, who were ſo like their Father in the features of the face, the ſtrength of arm, and magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of heart. Kinde receptions, praiſes, and congratulations, would have never had an end, if the General, who moſt paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately deſired to thank again his gratious Creatour, had not, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king an occaſion from the time, (the night now coming on very faſt) after his thanks to every one for their kindneſs, moſt cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly and dexterouſly diſmiſs'd them.</p>
               <p>After their departure, <hi>Euſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius</hi> left onely with his Wife and his Sons, began to ſay to them, Ah Wife, ah Sons, as dear to my heart, as all the hope it hath, and all its felicity; and
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:46454:85"/>what ſenſe have we of the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of favours ſo mercifull a God beſtows upon us? Ah dear <hi>Theopiſta,</hi> whom ſo long I have ſigh'd for, behold me again in thy arms; I embrace thee by the favour of that moſt loving Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who moſt gratiouſly and mercifully depriv'd me of thee, to make me reliſh pleaſure, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring thee to me. And O ye Sons, ſo principal a part of my bowels, have ye in ſuch diſatrous and difficult wayes of hoſtile vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſſitudes kept the innocence was due from you by gratitude, not onely by nature, for the many obligations, which more than all men living beſides, ye have to ſo bountifull a God? Embrace ye me, O Sons, O Sons much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fir'd, and twice born. O how many times have tears drown'd my ſleep, when I thought I heard you howling and roaring in the
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:46454:85"/>Woods? But glory be to God, we behold one another once again, and ſhall meet for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture more happily, for the plenty of ſo many favours cannot chooſe but ſo mollify, and ſo powerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the end raiſe our hearts to correſpond with God Almighty, but that this correſpondence, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flaming, and repleniſhing us with him, muſt ſhowre on our ſouls a Paradſie of graces, of glory, and happineſs.</p>
               <p>Here he made an end, for affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction brake the thread of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; <hi>Theopiſta</hi> wept, &amp; his Sons likewiſe wept. The brother the brother, the husband the wife, the mother the ſons, and the ſons now their father, now their mother did hug, and embrace, mixing congra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulations with kiſſes, and embitte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their kiſſes with tears. Every thing concluded in expreſſions of kindneſs, and the muteſt were
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:46454:86"/>moſt eloquent. All theſe love-extaſies they ended at the foot of a Crucifix, where what diſcourſes of gratitude, what ſenſe of devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, what affections of affection, and what proteſtations, and reſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations they made, I cannot deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe. The Angells have done it, who, ſpectators of ſo delicate and wonderfull a ſcene, have regiſtred their Acts in the Annals of eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, to preſent them to God, as a pleaſing ſight to him who is in his own ſphear, when he ſhines among the flames of an enamour'd heart.</p>
               <p>They ſupt, but gaz'd more than they did eat, the communication of their miſeryes paſt refreſhing them more, than the delicateſt meat, though it had been dreſt by the skilfulleſt hand, and with the rareſt ſauces in the world.</p>
               <p>In the morning they went to the Army, which rendevous'd toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:46454:86"/>expected them, waving with gladneſs, acclamations, and ſuch joyfull applauſe, that it plainly appeared the happineſs alone of the Generall, was the ſoul of that vaſt body, conſidering his digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but the heart, if we conſider their affections.</p>
               <p>This day they were jocund and joviall, and conſumed the next in preparations to be gone, the word being given through the Campe of their future diſlodging. <hi>Euſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius,</hi> when the legions, the bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage, and priſoners were marcht away, went directly to <hi>Rome,</hi> in the midway to which he received advice, that <hi>Trajan,</hi> the juſt, the valiant, and couragious, was dead, which diſturb'd in ſome ſort the contentment of his heart. Something ſhould be ſaid in the praiſe of his vertue, if the name of <hi>Trajan</hi> had not been the greateſt prayſe the memorialls of that age
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:46454:87"/>could commemorate. The Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall publiſht the news to the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, who wept not for his death, for at the ſame time, they heard of the ſucceſſion of <hi>Adrian,</hi> not was it lawfull, or at leaſt ſecure to weep, when tears might mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly be interpreted, and ſaid to be ſhed, rather for the coronation of the one, than the death of the other. In thoſe tyrannous times, they lookt not, nor ſpake without counſell, and before they went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, receiv'd information of the intereſts of the Prince, to know what kind of Countenance they ſhould wear through the City.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euſtachius</hi> arriving in <hi>Rome,</hi> was receiv'd in that manner by the Emperour, that he found no want of <hi>Trajan.</hi> I relate not the ceremonyes at his meeting, his prayſes, the concourſes of people, the Images, Crowns, and trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phall arches, becauſe in each
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:46454:87"/>place, where vertue appears, ſhe draggs triumphs after her, and he's much more fortunate than valiant, whoſe vertue can receive augmentation of glory by a tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adrian</hi> embraced, commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and rewarded him, augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his titles, his riches, and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. <hi>Adrian</hi>'s whole diſcourſe ſtill concluded with the prudence, the valour, and fortune of <hi>Placi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus. Placidus</hi> was the Emperors right hand, the apple of the eye of the Empire, and a patterne for the Lords. All lookt on him, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as a valiant Commander, but a favorite, He that of <hi>Placidus</hi> could diſpoſe whoſe Genius was ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed predominant o're <hi>Adrians,</hi> thought he could command the Prince: <hi>Adrian</hi> made him often tell the ſtory of his life, and kiſt, and hugg'd him often in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and ſometimes was ſo jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous,
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:46454:88"/>and ſometimes ſo delighted with him, that he challenging a ſhare in the fortunate ſucceſſe of ſo raging a tempeſt, ſaid, in the health of <hi>Placidus,</hi> he ow'd his firſt triumph to the Gods.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Placidus</hi> diſpatcht all affaires, and calm'd and reſolv'd all the Emperours cares, and doubts. But what wonder is't, that vertue ſhould be lov'd, and reſpected. <hi>Placidus</hi> never went into the Royall Cabinet, but learning, and truth enterd with him, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary conditions for the <hi>Moſes,</hi> who is to be there to diſcourſe with his God. His Power never ſwell'd him at all, and though in ſo ſhort a ſpace of time, he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd to ſuch greatneſs, that his looks and command were held in the ſame veneration, yet he more humble, and more affable to all than before, then onely ſhew'd his greatneſs, when he had an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:46454:88"/>to ſhew his magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity. He had a heart of aſhes, and ſtill thought upon his own vileneſs. As the Bee that the wind ſhould not carry him away, he ſtill carry'd in his hands the baſe ſtone of his condition. He had not, like <hi>Philotas,</hi> need of ſhoes ſoal'd with lead, to the end the winde of vanity, ſhould not raiſe him from the earth. Death, and the Croſs, were the Anchor and Maſt, which ſecured this Ship. He knew well the feathers of birds, that were offer'd up in holocauſts, were thrown on the dunghill, and that the more the Syren of great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs allures, the more needfull it is for <hi>Ulyſſes,</hi> to be ty'd to the maſt, for his own preſervation.</p>
               <p>The greater his power was, the more ſtil the followers, or to ſpeak better, the fiſhers of Fortune ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended their netts, and toyl'd for his favour. Every one believ'd, he
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:46454:89"/>had ſtopt the rowling wheele of his fortune, when he thought, he was ſure of his power. Every one directed his motions to the ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour of this light, which was reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renc'd by all, as the North Star of this Heaven. O with what eaſe do our eys deceive themſelves!</p>
               <p>Whither it be the nature of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, whoſe heat's the leſs du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, by being the more vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or whither it be the nature of nature, which having to every thing preſcribed a mutation, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces that faſter to the center, which ſhe hath with greater vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence exalted to the ſummit, <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidus</hi> had a fall.</p>
               <p>Confide he in the favour of man, who is a greater favourit, more deſerving, and more neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to his maſter, than <hi>Placidus</hi> was to <hi>Adrian.</hi> He fell, but he fell into Paradiſe. This is a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate precipice, for he fell into
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:46454:89"/>the lap of eternall and incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible felicity, but yet tis a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipice, for a terrible and dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full example of human mutabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</p>
               <p>That a man for his vertue reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, and for his condition moſt powerfull, well ſpoken of by all, deſir'd by all Nations, and victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in all battailes, whom his Countrey glory'd in, the age he liv'd in honour'd, and in whom the Prince ſaid he was happy, ſhould ſet in an inſtant, be exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd by a hangman, unjuſtly condemn'd and ſentenc'd by that mouth, which more than any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther careſt, kiſt, and made him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown'd, is a thing ſo full of hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, that I hold the man mad, who after ſo notorious an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, will truſt in his own prudence, and think it ſufficient to ſupport him in the favour of man, be he never ſo friendly, or oblig'd.</p>
               <pb n="168" facs="tcp:46454:90"/>
               <p>The ancient Roman Emperors, after any remarkable victory gave publiquely thanks to their Gods, which they uſed to do with that pompe of apparrell, and train of applauſes, that many times the altars had occaſion to envy their bravery, who offer'd Incenſe on them, and ſtill he was ador'd more devoutly that diſcharged the vow, than he that had given the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe.</p>
               <p>The pompe predeſign'd for the glory of this ſacrifice, receiving the Period expected ſo long, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drian</hi> with bravery more becoming a magnificent oftentation, than a devout and great gratitude, repay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the Temple to give the Gods thanks, for the Empire ſo great, and victory ſo glorious they propitiouſly had given him. He went into the Temple, atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and applauded by all his greateſt Princes, beginning his
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:46454:90"/>function with the accuſtomed pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the fortunate, who uſually place all their devotion in the charge they are at in the ſacrifice. When the end drew nigh, he loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king about him, remembred that <hi>Placidus</hi> was not there, and ſighing, quickly feard, leſt ſome ſudden diſtemper might ſurprize him in that manner, as to hinder him from waiting upon him.</p>
               <p>He ſaid to himſelf, he cannot be ingratefull, to whoſe only glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the victory we conſecrate is due; nor can he be thought irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, for he is well known and reſpected, as deſcended from as holy a man as Heaven hath on earth, and he will not degenerate. The ſacrifice no ſooner was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but the Emperour with extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary kindnes, was extreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſirous to know what had happen'd to his <hi>Placidus,</hi> who as ſoon as he came into the Temple (not without a univerſall aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment)
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:46454:91"/>he heard, departed thence in great haſt with his ſons.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adrian</hi> more doubtfull than before, and more irreſolute, gave order, that <hi>Placidus</hi> ſhould again be ſought after, and if he were well, ſhould repaire unto him, who ſtayd to ſpeak with him, with unſpeakable anxiety. The Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour ſcarce arriv'd at the Palace, when <hi>Placidus</hi> appeared with his ſons, and <hi>Adrian</hi> ſoon looking ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renely complained of him, as if it had troubl'd him much, to be ſo long uncertain of his health whom he loved, and favoured in that manner.</p>
               <p>And what could I think (he quickly ſaid to him) but that you were ill, ſince you were not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at the ſacrifice, we offer'd to the Gods, out of gratitude for a victory, which more for the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of your glory, than the growth
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:46454:91"/>of the Roman Empire, they ſo prodigally have favour'd, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted. Surely ſomething of great conſequence (to the ſtanders by great ſcandall) made thee go from the Temple, where the Gods would have hath thee to be grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully religious, and exemplar.</p>
               <p>Sir, reply'd <hi>Placidus,</hi> you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe me of a fault I never commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. If becauſe I was not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, where cold, mute, and impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſtones are ador'd, you think me ingratefull to Chriſt, who on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is the giver of victoryes, you gueſs very ill.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adrian</hi> at theſe words, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther amaz'd, or ambiguous, I know not, looking on the ground, and with the forefinger of his right hand, ſcratching lightly his hair, ſtood ſtill a little while, like one that thinks on things, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves not what to do, then dying his countenance with his doubts,
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:46454:92"/>he bluſht, and grew pale, began, and was ſilent. In the end, he compoſing himſelf as well as he could, ſent out of his mouth, which expreſs'd indignation, theſe words, or the like.</p>
               <p>Let's be cautious, O <hi>Placidus,</hi> of ſpeaking againſt Heaven, for the matter is too nice. Jeſting is not good, where ſimplicity or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignity ill apply'd, may occaſion bad examples to the publique. Though the knowledge men have of thy goodneſs, ſecures thee from the fear of being reputed irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, thou ſhouldſt not bring me into the danger of blame, for too much forbearance, by permitting ſuch things to be ſpoken in my preſence, which cannot be peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly heard, without the blaſphemy of the ear.</p>
               <p>Sir, reply'd <hi>Euſtachius,</hi> grown red with the holy Ghoſt, whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever profeſſes his Religion, does
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:46454:92"/>jeſt. For the Victories I have had, I have thank'd the gratious God that beſtows them. If I waited not on you where <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> are adored, 'twas onely that I could not endure to ſee, not onely vainly, but wickedly, the incenſes conſum'd, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the Lord of Hell, where <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> themſelves are eternally tormented.</p>
               <p>O God, what do I hear? Is <hi>Placidus</hi> ſo terrible a Blaſphemer? <hi>Placidus</hi> ſo pertinacious a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian? A Chriſtian, and Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, even to my face? Fear we ſo little the Thunderbolts of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven? Is <hi>Adrian</hi>'s Sword and Juſtice ſo ſlenderly regarded? Souldiers, keep him in hold, his greatneſs will ſerve to get For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune renown. Some violent di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction of minde hath perhaps overcome him, and therefore give him time and opportunity to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collect
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:46454:93"/>himſelf. A ſacrifice will rectify his errour, and when no hope is left, I'le finde out a way to repair the veneration of the Gods, and ſave the Law from violence. No greatneſs of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, prerogative of Valour, or protection of Favour, is ſecurity to any that refuſes to worſhip our Gods, during <hi>Adrian</hi>'s reign. Shut him up again, and keep him ſafe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Placidus</hi> would have anſwer'd; but the violence of <hi>Adrian</hi>'s paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which carried him away, made him loſe that opportunity. In the mean time, the Souldiers ſurrounded him, while he full of ſpirit, began to preach, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly profeſs his belief, deteſting the Idols, and preaching the truth of Chriſts Law to all the Guard of <hi>Ceſar.</hi> Yet none was ſo bold to approach to offend him; ſo powerfully the rayes of his Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue,
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:46454:93"/>which commanded a reſpect in each perſon, were darted by him.</p>
               <p>Why delay ye, Fellow-Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, he mildly ſpake to them, why do ye delay? Is this the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline you learnt in my School? Obey ye ſo ſlowly your Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral? What reſpect retards you? Is't perhaps to do me honour? Honour me by imitating the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs with which I have alwayes obey'd my Superiours. A Maſter's commands ſhould be executed, not examin'd. Approach free'y to me, I defend not my ſelf, I long have aſpir'd to theſe Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. Behold here are my hands, binde them if you pleaſe, I refuſe not to be ty'd: He was bound harder, and more ignominiouſly, for whoſe ſake ignominies ſhall be glorious to me, and wounds ſerve for trophyes. In one thing alone ye may gratifie the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:46454:94"/>I have alwayes had for you, if ye ſpeedily ſend to <hi>Adrian,</hi> and tell him I am <hi>Euſtachius,</hi> not <hi>Placidus,</hi> a Profeſſor of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, no Idolater; and that if from me, my Wife, or my Sons, he hope for any other confeſſion, he hopes for it in vain. He ſhall ſee by our undauntedneſs, what manner of Gods he ſerves, who loves his God as heartily as we do love ours: and if he'll deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine any thing on our lives, who ſo firmly perſiſt in our faith, let him ſpeedily do it, to decline the loſs of time in his Counſels, and retard not the reward of our Victories.</p>
               <p>Theſe words being ſpoken with a ſtable and fearleſs countenance, begat an amazement in the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors, which turned in the end into pity. Every one was ſorry for him; and there was not any perſon ſo vile, that would not
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:46454:94"/>very willingly have open'd a vein, to avoyd ſeeing him brought to ſo ill an end, who was as good as happy, and ſo happy, that he could deſire nothing of Fortune, becauſe ſhe had nothing left to give him.</p>
               <p>When the rumour was ſpread through the City, that <hi>Placidus</hi> was carry'd to Priſon, the People abſhed, came running with ſuch tacit confuſion, that the ſtreets; though full of Perſons, would have been ſuppos'd a Deſart, if they had given credit to their ears, the tumult here making no noyſe, and quietneſs not repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. The ſilence was ſuch as is uſually occaſion'd by abundance of fear, or a ſorrow incapable of revenge. The cauſe of this ſtrangeneſs was both terrible and ambiguous to them, who could not think him impious that was ſo well known, now excuſe a
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:46454:95"/>wicked deed of a Prince ſo much fear'd.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adrian</hi> inform'd with what conſtancy <hi>Euſtachius</hi> contemn'd both Death, and the Gods, was mad with indignation, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps too with grief, for without extream violence we paſs not to hatred from love; ſo deeply and tacitly this potent affection of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection takes root in our hearts. Suppoſing himſelf to be vilify'd and deſpis'd, as he was contriving a revenge, a new information furpriz'd him, that <hi>Theopiſta,</hi> with her ſons, was as ready to accompany her Husband into Priſon, as ſhe did in his Belief. He heard that all four, unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly and publickly deteſting the Idols, (not without the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples wonder and attention) ſtood preaching and extolling the merit of their Religion. He, (over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by a violent paſſion) which
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:46454:95"/>tranſported him againſt them, would precipitouſly have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded their preſent execution, if ſome perſons of authority, commiſerating the ſadneſs of their caſe, and endeavouring the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſing of his fury, had not made him believe, 'twould be more ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous to the Empire, and Religion, to conquer <hi>Euſtachius,</hi> than kill him. They repreſented to <hi>Adrian, Euſtachius</hi> was a Perſon belov'd of the People, and Armies, and 'twas neceſſary, not onely commendable, to give him ſome time, that his contumacy might juſtifie the puniſhment, or repentance make glorious his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment. This, as the beſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, was concluded; and therefore the Priſoner was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd, he ſhould prepare himſelf to make the Gods a ſacrifice, or be ſacrific'd himſelf. This com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate continued three dayes, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:46454:96"/>which time, all the Chriſtians of the City were not wanting to viſit him, to comfort and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage him. His friends us'd all means for his ſafety, and the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour invaded him by his inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate acquaintance. The laſt temptation was ſuggeſted by a Friend, who, though ſent by <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi> feign'd he came of himſelf out of kindneſs, and an earneſt deſire to preſerve him; inſomuch as what Arts the School ſels, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling can counterfeit, or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt deviſe, he put in execution; and making a mixture of affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of arguments, offers, and threats, and tempering and infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing each thing in commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the laſt and moſt powerfull enchantment to Perſons of Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, labour'd mightily to corrupt him.</p>
               <p>Deareſt <hi>Euſtachius,</hi> what is become of thy renowned Virtue,
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:46454:96"/>the ſcourge of our Enemies, the prop of our Empire, and glory of our Age? Who hath perſwaded thee to make thy ſelf an Enemy to the Gods, by oppoſing the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of thy Anceſtors, the Law of thy Prince, and injuring the ſimplicity of the People, who by thy example will protect the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries done to the Gods, which have made thee victorious againſt all the powers, and triumphant under that ſpace of Heaven they govern and illuminate? <hi>Euſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius,</hi> thou diſſenteſt from thy ſelf, not onely from thy Prince, and out faith. Why leav'ſt thou the Religion thou ſo frequently haſt defended with thy dangers, ſo often augmented with victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and ſo many times authoriz'd with thy noble and ſumptuous ſacrifices, even to the exhauſting of thy Treaſure? Is this the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude thou profeſſeſt to the Gods,
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:46454:97"/>who ſo often have made thee vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious, and ſharing, as it were, their Divinity with thee, have allow'd men as well to ſwear by thy happineſs, as by their own omnipotency.</p>
               <p>Some Devil, and Enemy to the People of <hi>Rome,</hi> hath perverted thee. The juſtice of thoſe Gods, who never abandon'd thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, till they ſaw thee their Enemy, make thee ſee the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice of thy cauſe. Conſider, dear Friend, what condition thou art in; from the high way of triumphs, and greatneſs, thou art faln into Priſon, and the danger of thy head; Ah unhappy man, who will aſſiſt thee? Will that God peradventure, whoſe own hands are nail'd? Wilt thou therefore diſhonour the glory of thy name, ruine thy ſtate, and the greatneſs of thy Family, and bury the hopes of thy Country,
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:46454:97"/>which promis'd it ſelf, in thy va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and prudence, a long and ſure prop to its happineſs? Wilt thou deſpiſe the fortune which offers it ſelf unto thee by the favour of the Prince, who, becauſe he might not ſee thee deſtroy'd, exhibites to make thee ſo great, that thou in all the world ſhalt have none above thee, he onely excepted, who is ſecond to none that is not a God. All thy friends and alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, with tears and proſtrate hearts, beſeech thee not to do it. Wilt thou ſee ſo many tears ſhed in vain, and ſo many friends de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, for a God condemn'd, and puniſh'd? They have bought thy protection with the ſweat of their labours, and have ſpent, and ſtill paſſionately deſire to ſpend their blood for the glory of thy Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Name; and wilt thou give conſent to abandon them? Ah, they may have reaſon to fear it,
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:46454:98"/>if thou tak'ſt delight in holding them ſo long in ſuſpence, and go'ſt about even to abandon the Gods themſelves. But who, but who are they, which remov'd not far from thee, groan under the weight of ſo many Chains, in ſo dark and ſo dreadfull a Priſon? Ah wretch that I am, whom do I behold? Are they, or are they not the ſame? Are thoſe thy ſo valorous Sons, and that thy Wife ſo chaſt, whom thou ſo much lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedſt? Ah <hi>Placidus,</hi> and canſt finde in thy heart to ſee them torn in pieces? And why grow'ſt thou ſo cruelly perverſe on the ſudden to thy Friends, thy Wife, thy Sons, thy ſelf, and the Gods of thy Progenitors, of thy Prince, thy Country, and Triumphs?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euſtachius</hi> inſpired by God, turning himſelf towards his Sons with a ſmile, leſt his valour might be ſtain'd if he fell to
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:46454:98"/>words, when he had the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of his Sword, ſpake to them in this manner.</p>
               <p>We muſt now, my Beloved, reſolve to do ſomething; and what will ye do? To enjoy a ſhort eternity, will ye diſguſt the Friends which counſel us ſo well? For a God, though a Creator and Redeemer, will ye offend a Prince, that hath done you the honour to let you ſpill ſo often your blood, to uphold him in his Throne? For a God diſpleas'd with our loving Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, though Heaven be his Temple, and by nature he be goodneſs it ſelf, and virtually omnipotent, ſhall we leave off offering up Incenſe to theſe beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull Statues, where men admire the excellency of Art, and harken to infernal Conſultations? If ye'll reſolve on this, beſides the leave ye'll have of the moſt gratious
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:46454:99"/>Prince, to ſpill again your blood for his ſake; he will too permit you, (ſince the loſs of your ſouls is inevitable, if ye dye in rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt the true God) to live at leaſt, and quickly leade a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate life, if it be a happy life, to have many occaſions of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting with the dangers and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries of war, emulation, envy, ſickneſs, and ſervitude.</p>
               <p>So ſpake he to them; then turning himſelf to his idolatrous Counſellour, he added; I both excuſe and pity thee: Thou doſt not comprehend what our ſouls aſpire to; we thirſt after favours and lives which are not terreſtrial. Report, we do not adore Gods, Deflowrers of Virgins, Inceſtuous to their Siſters, and Deceivers of Men; Gods that are Parricides, Adulterers, Rapacious, Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, and Blood-ſuckers, born to the ſhame, not protection of the
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:46454:99"/>world, and deify'd onely by them, who under the ſhadow of a Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that loves, and does not pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh impieties, ſeek to ſhelter their conſciences. And is't poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible a Man of Valour, though no Chriſtian, ſhould not be aſham'd to ſee himſelf proſtrate at the foot of a God, more wicked than wickedneſs it ſelf? And is't poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible he ſhould not know theſe Incenſes are conſum'd in vain; and ſo many, and ſuch charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Victims, are to no other end, but to waſte our Wealth and Goods? Theſe are Gods which rob us, though dead, and though ador'd. O blindneſs! That God is not ours, which ſeeks our perdition; and that God is no God, that knows not how to hinder his own. Let us beſtow our incenſes where we have our hopes. We hope not in impieties, in wickedneſſes, and
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:46454:100"/>eternal blaſphemers of Gods name, by whom they condemn'd, will alwayes feel the puniſhment of their pride and rebellion.</p>
               <p>I can anſwer you no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, but that you know us not, if you threaten us. And what wouldſt thou have us to fear? Shame? And think'ſt thou that he'll dye of ſhame, who, a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour of the Devil, and the World, dyes ſerving, and to ſerve his Creator? What would'ſt thou have us fear? Death? A Chriſtian hopes for death, and fears it not. Gods knife, not <hi>Adrians,</hi> affrights us. A Chriſtian hath his Country, his faith, hope, treaſures, and glory in Heaven. He is not a Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of this life. Whoſoever kils him, does not drive him from the Earth, but helps him to get ſooner to Heaven, whither he (here a Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grim) aſpires. O unhappy man, that to live a few days, would loſe ſuch
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:46454:100"/>a fortunate occaſion of eternally beatifying himſelf. But why nam'd I a few days? If thou canſt aſſure me of a moment of time for ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficing to thy Gods, I am ready to tell thee, I will readily do it: but if that cannot be, (ſo fading and uncertain is this our frail life) why wouldſt thou make me loſe an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal felicity for a very ſhort mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of time? for a moment uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain? for a moment, which, if cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, would have howſoever more torment than life? Friend, we will dye, even to fly this ſo troubleſome life, much more to ſerve our God, that is ſo full of power. And this life is too vile, too uncertain, and too dependant; and we paſſionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſire once to dye, to behold our moſt mercifull God, to whoſe one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſence our ſouls do aſpire and ſigh. Ah, O my Sons, ſhall we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver attain to this happineſs? Shall we never get to taſt it? O moſt happy we, if our God will be
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:46454:101"/>pleas'd to confer it on us. And what ſhall we do in that bleſſed light, which never is eclipſed? In that inexhauſtible and incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible Sea of delights, and conſolations? Will theſe petty diſaſters we ſuffer for his ſake, prove bitter or ſweet, profitable or ſad? Ah woe's me, a frail and poor Creature, who love not even ſo well my God, but that the fleſh makes me think of intereſt, of pleaſure, and reward. Be not ſcandaliz'd my ſons, let's fight, let's ſuffer, and dye for the onely love of God. God alone be our object, our reward, and our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt. Though he did not intend to reward us, he deſerves to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lov'd; and how much for us hath he done? Ah ſcourges, ah thorns, ah lances, ah nails, and ah croſs, ye know very well.</p>
               <p>They ſpake here all together, as expreſſing the conſent of four valiant perſons, who animating
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:46454:101"/>one another, as they fortify'd themſelves, ſo made the Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors relent. The Orator, confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and unable to compaſs his end, returned to <hi>Adrian,</hi> relating to him, he had met with a Priſon full of Conſtancy; where he that expected to dye, was more fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of the flowneſs, than the ſharpneſs of his Sword.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adrian</hi> implacably incens'd with this laſt relation, calling <hi>Placidus</hi> ingratefull, ſacrilegious, and ſeditious, and invoking par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly each God, extoll'd and exaggerated the merit of his own piety. That he had rather part with a Miniſter of ſtate, though uſefull and glorious to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, than that Heaven ſhould be ſacrific'd to by his hand. When he with exclamations, complaints, threats, and injuries, had ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently enflam'd and tormented himſelf, (the authority of the Devil his Counſellor prevailing
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:46454:102"/>at laſt) he reſolv'd to blot <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidus</hi> out of the book of life; and ask'd by his will, what death they ſhould dye; the Lions, he reply'd, ſhould devour them, who had for that purpoſe faſted three dayes together.</p>
               <p>The innocent Chriſtians were led to the Theater, whither they went with a faith deſerving a Theater. The People (who with tears reſented their condition) ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company'd and pitied them with a ſorrow and compaſſion that cannot be expreſs'd. Every one was ſorry for the Sons unhappy youth, and every one for the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents affliction. Some thought the death of the young men was moſt worthy of pity, becauſe they were cut off in the flower of their age, while others had a greater compaſſion for the Parents, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing their death to be the more pretious, for by loſing themſelves, and their Sons, they loſt and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:46454:102"/>more lives. When the Theater was open'd, and the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons condemned appear'd, who more cheer'd up themſelves in their dangers, no eye was free from tears, eſpecially when they ſaw, and heard <hi>Euſtachius</hi> ſpeak, who kneeling in the midſt of his beloved family, cry'd aloud with his hands rear'd to Heaven.</p>
               <p>Though all hell ſhould be let looſe, much leſs a few Lyons, he can have no feare that loves thee, O Lord. Thou art too ſweet, and too dear, O ſweet and dear Love of our love. Behold us at thy feer, moſt ready and prepar'd for a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, which is not ſo pure, and immaculate, as thou doſt deſerve, is what four poor, and miſerable ſinners can give thee. With thy loving mercyes, make it what thou would'ſt have it to be for thy glory. What ſay ye dear Sons? are ye glad of this occaſion, to ſhew your prompt obedience, to
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:46454:103"/>our moſt gracious Father and God. Take ye pleaſure that he ſee, he hath not given ſo much to you, but that ye are ready to preſent, and ſacrifice more to him, if it lay in your power? Offer up to him, and give him that life, he ſo often hath beſtow'd upon you, preſerv'd and made noble. Which way will theſe Lyons come out? Will they make peradventure to this place? Come valorous Sons, let us bend thither. Ye are well acquainted with Lyons, ye have conquer'd them formerly, when ye were not old enough to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh them: Will ye now be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of them, when ye fight for Gods ſake?</p>
               <p>Ah dear husband (his wife in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupting him began) wrong not the valour of our Sons. Ye, O my Sons ſhall ſtand here together, and I here before: She will lead you out of this life, who brought you into it. Give prayſes to God
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:46454:103"/>for the victory, and bleſs and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke him. O holy, thrice holy, and a thouſand times holy, behold us at the ſacrifice, we ſo often have deſir'd. Accept O amorous, accept moſt loving flame of our breaſts, this litte and laſt, but cordiall oblation of our wiſh.</p>
               <p>When the grates were open'd, the Lyons (very hungry and at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty) iſſu'd forth, whoſe horrible roaring made all the ſpectators af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid, for they came with that violence and fury, that the holy Martyrs obſequies were lamented by all, e're their death. None could endure to behold this deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, ſo as with a generous aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, all lookt another way, not now not to pity, but to ſhun the the firſt encounter of ſo ſad, and ſo skreaking a compaſſion. Now every one, diſliking ſo mercileſs a ſpectacle, departed, abhorring and deteſting ſo barbarous a cruelty,
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:46454:104"/>when behold a ſudden hiſſing ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, each eye was recall'd to the Theater, and o'recome with the wonder of an accident, which diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order'd, and terrifi'd each breaſt, and each conſcience.</p>
               <p>When the Lyons were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chain'd, and came furiouſly to the grate, which was ſet wide open, they no ſooner approached to the prey, but fearfull, harmleſs, and hungry, retreated, and carrying low their heads, (ſhewing they were conquer'd by the vertue of men, who though living on earth, were of Heaven) perſwaded the people to magnify Gods power, who not onely when he pleaſes, makes Lyons, but the pillars them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that bear up the Heavens, tremble, totter, and ſhake.</p>
               <p>In the moſt noble fabrique of the Temple of <hi>Solomon,</hi> I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber not, that in any of the Chapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, or baſes of braffe were figur'd
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:46454:104"/>certain knobs, compoſed of Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubins, of Lyons, and Palme-trees. Behold here a myſtery verifi'd. <hi>Euſtachius, Theopiſtas</hi> and their Sons, repreſenting four Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins, with the branches of Palme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trees adorning their hands, came conquerours out of the midſt of thoſe Lyons, whom ſtill with great eaſe, the ſervants of God have uſually o'recome, as if they were Lambs, and not Lyons. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drian,</hi> to whom the relation of the miracle was brought with all ſpeed, poyſon'd with the fury of his vilifi'd Devill, lifting his hands towards Heaven, and feigning he was comforted, that he might not confeſs he was o'recome. O Eternall Providence, brake forth, even the beaſts themſelves abhor thoſe ill-bred People, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell'd againſt the Gods. The Lyon never ſhew'd his magnanimity more ſeaſonably, than by ſcorning
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:46454:105"/>ſuch wicked, and infamous nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment. But let them not brag, their ſacriledges were unpuniſh'd, for my ſword is keen enough, to roote out of the world ſo peſtife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous a graffe. I muſt not let the Peoples ſimplicity be deluded by their incantations, who that they might detract from the glory of our Gods, have made hell protect their impiety. Remove them from the Theater.</p>
               <p>The next morning the Tyrant aroſe by break of day, whoſe fury would not ſuffer him to reſt. He was very much afflicted, to ſee his vaſt Empire inferiour in valour, to the courage of four perſons, arm'd with nothing els, but the only name of JESUS.</p>
               <p>The ancient Emperors, to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrize the Chriſtians, kept a huge brazen Bull, the invention I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve of ſome Devill, who brought a hell on earth, which when 'twas
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:46454:105"/>red hot by a vehement fire, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted and terrifi'd whoſoeve beheld it.</p>
               <p>This machine expoſed in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, which ſcar'd even him, that went neer to it, the barbarous Tyrant gave command, the four Champions ſhould be put, and encloſed in it's bulke. O number proportion'd to the forme of a ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis, whoſe quadrangular firmeneſs was moſt fit, to ſupport the grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Church.</p>
               <p>This liker a Devill, than a Bull, was no ſooner made hot, but dreadfully at his eyes, his mouth, and his noſtrills, breathing ſmoak, and flames, was ſufficient to terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy, even heaven it ſelf, much more the poor breaſt of a man, whom the meer apprehenſion of d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th was enough to deterre and deject. Thoſe breathings, which in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry other creature were the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of life, were in this infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:46454:106"/>monſter the ſymptomes of death. While the Machine waxed hot, the matter enflaming it ſelf (which naturally being cold, by how much the more vigorouſly it reſiſted the heat, by ſo much the more violently receiv'd and diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted the heat with more paine) I imagine to my ſelf, the priſoner firſt aſſaulted by the aire, which with its heat invading his head; did threaten to choake him. That part of the braſſe then growing more vehemently hot, which nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt the fire, endur'd the firſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults, the poor tormented crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, beginning firſt to feele his fleſh ſinge, then fry, and conſume, could not chooſe (grown offenſive to himſelf) but grieve he was forc'd to bewayle with unſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable ſorrow, the cruelty of that puniſhment, which making him ſurvive his own fleſh, caus'd him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſee thoſe limbs, which ſo cruelly
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:46454:106"/>(O death even painfull to our phancy) he had both felt die, and was forc'd to lament too when dead.</p>
               <p>No ſooner the cruell Emperors Command was perform'd, but the fire being lighted, in leſs than an houre, the Bull (which no longer was of braſs, but all fire) threw up horrible ſparkles from out of the midſt of the ambient flames, with ſo dolefull a ſpectacle, that the ſtanders by themſelves, felt their boſomes and eyes melt with pity, at the ſight of that object, which certainly without griefe, was not to be ſeen.</p>
               <p>Our four couragious Champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were ſacrific'd to truth, on this altar of torments, whoſe affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate death I reſolv'd to conceal, ſince I feel my heart broken to pieces, I would I could ſay with devotion, but I am ſo great a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, I dare not have ſuch thoughts of my ſelf.</p>
               <pb n="202" facs="tcp:46454:107"/>
               <p>I confeſs I abandon thee, O Reader, in the beſt of the ſtory, ſince I ſhould have repreſented the devotion, with which theſe holy Martyrs have yielded up the Ghoſts, beſeeching God to free them at laſt from theſe earthly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, and make beneficiall to the piety of poſterity, the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of theſe ſufferings, of which the firſt reward, was to hear a voyce ſpeaking from Heaven to them, it ſhall be, as ye deſire, O happy ſoules.</p>
               <p>I confeſs I ſhould relate, how gloriouſly Gods omnipotence ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd, by freeing them from ſo terrible a burning, where they were rather lulled aſleep than conſum'd, without the leaſt harm of a hair, much leſs of their gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments or fleſh.</p>
               <p>I confeſs, it would redound ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much to our profit, to meditate on the pity (to our own confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion)
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:46454:107"/>which an unbelieving people afforded by their tears, of which the moſt wicked commiſerated their puniſhment, and the beſt their faith did imitate. I confeſs all this, but what ſhall I do? my pen can write no more, grown feeble with compaſſion, as well as with wearineſs.</p>
               <p>I have ſpent all my affections, it remaines now, O Reader, thou begin to uſe thine. And when e're again (before it be too late) wilt thou have ſuch a fair opportunity to meditate, to weep, and to lead a better life.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
